<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discovery of the man of sin, acting in a mystery of iniquitie, pleading for his kingdom, against the coming of Christ to take away sin. Or, an answer to a book set forth by Tho. Weld of Gateshead, Richard Prideaux, Sam. Hamond, Will. Cole, and Will. Durant of Newcastle. By way of reply to an answer of James Nayler's to their former book, called The perfect Pharisee: who call themselves ministers of Christ, but are found ministring for the kingdom of Antichrist. Published for clearing the innocency of the truth from their malicious slanders, and discovering their deceits. By one whom the world calls James Nayler.</title>
            <author>Naylor, James, 1617?-1660.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 145 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89836</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N274</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E738_16</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202155</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862551</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862551</idno>
            <idno type="VID">114714</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89836)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 114714)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 113:E738[16])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discovery of the man of sin, acting in a mystery of iniquitie, pleading for his kingdom, against the coming of Christ to take away sin. Or, an answer to a book set forth by Tho. Weld of Gateshead, Richard Prideaux, Sam. Hamond, Will. Cole, and Will. Durant of Newcastle. By way of reply to an answer of James Nayler's to their former book, called The perfect Pharisee: who call themselves ministers of Christ, but are found ministring for the kingdom of Antichrist. Published for clearing the innocency of the truth from their malicious slanders, and discovering their deceits. By one whom the world calls James Nayler.</title>
                  <author>Naylor, James, 1617?-1660.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 51, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Giles Calvert, at the black Spread-Eagle neer the west-end of Pauls.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to: Weld, Thomas.  The perfect Pharisee under monkish holinesse, opposing the fundamentall principles of the doctrine of the Gospel, and Scripture-practices of Gospel-worship manifesting himselfe in the generation of men called Quakers.</note>
                  <note>The names "Tho. Weld .. Newcastle." are enclosed in a complex system of brackets on title page.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June. 3.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Weld, Thomas, 1590?-1662. --  Perfect Pharisee under monkish holinesse, opposing the fundamentall principles of the doctrine of the Gospel, and Scripture-practices of Gospel-worship manifesting himselfe in the generation of men called Quakers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:114714:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:114714:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DISCOVERY Of The Man of Sin, Acting in <hi>A Myſtery of Iniquitie,</hi> Pleading for his Kingdom, againſt the coming of Chriſt to take away Sin.</p>
            <p>OR, An ANSWER to a Book ſet forth BY
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Tho. Weld</hi> of Gateſhead,</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Richard Prideaux,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sam. Hamond</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Will. Cole,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>and <hi>Will. Durant</hi> of Newcaſtle.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>By way of Reply to an Anſwer of <hi>James Nayler</hi>'s to their former Book, called <hi>The Perfect Phariſee:</hi> Who call themſelves Miniſters of Chriſt, but are found miniſtring for the kingdom of Antichriſt.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed for clearing the innocency of the Truth from their malicious ſlanders, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering their deceits.</p>
            <p>By one whom the world calls <hi>James Nayler.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> at the black Spread-Eagle neer the weſt-end of <hi>Pauls.</hi> 1654.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:114714:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:114714:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O no mans wiſdom are we known, nor do we deſire by it to be approved; but to that in every ones Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience (which is the light of Chriſt) are we made manifeſt: and as that ariſes, by it ſhall we, and what we declare, be approved: and to that do we ſpeak in every one, to be known; and by that ſhall we eternally be witneſſed, when the book of Conſcience comes to be open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Now, Reader, to ſtrive for the maſtery by multitude of words, is not the way of the Spirit of God; nor wilt thou finde it practiſed in this Volume: but lyes and ſlanders are denied, and plain truth in few words is declared, not from the wiſdom of man, nor to the wiſdom of man, but for the ſimple ones ſake, in obedience to God, from a pure Conſcience, to ſtrengthen the ſimplicity, and of any pure deſires which may be in thy minde towards God. And if there be any thing (by the Spirit of the Lord) raiſed in thee, which convinces thee, and lets thee ſee how unprofitably thou haſt ſpent thy time in running from one man to another, (which call themſelves Miniſters) and hast got no true bread for thy ſoul, but art yet in thy fallen eſtate, thy carnal minde ruling, (which is death reigning.) And if thou haſt any deſire and hungerings after truth and righteouſneſs, wait upon the Lord in thy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, and in the light which convinces thee; and by the Lord ſhall thy ſoul be ſatisfied. And if there be in thee any ſimple honeſt deſires, to know who the falſe Prophets deceivers and ſeducers are, (which in this day of the Lord is to be revealed) go not to any man to know, but wait in the light which is in thy conſcience, which ſhews thee ſin in thy ſelf: which light will diſcover the man of ſin in the world; for that is
<pb facs="tcp:114714:3"/>
the brightneſs of his coming: and of this light every one hath a med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; (though theſe five, and all that love the deeds of darkneſs, who would not be diſcovered, ſtrongly deny it:) and ſuch are againſt Chriſt the light of the world: and there is Antichriſt diſcovered, and the man of ſin: and here in thy meaſure thou art partaker of the ſame light, by which theſe five and all their generation are diſcovered, and have been in all generations, by the children of light; and thereby are we ſeparated out of the kingdoms of the world, into the kingdom of Chriſt; for which they hate us, and would devour us: but <hi>Michael</hi> our Prince is riſen, and the war is begun with the Dragon, the Beaſt, and the falſe Prophet: but the Lamb ſhall take the victory; and wo unto them that are found upholding the Beaſt and the falſe Prophet: for he that help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and they that are holpen, ſhall fall together: for now the Lord is riſen, to be avenged of his enemies; and down they muſt, though their number be as the ſand of the ſea for multitude. Take heed whom you ſide with, you Powers of the earth.</p>
            <p>Friends, I was moved in my Anſwer to your <hi>Perfect Phariſee,</hi> at the end of it, to write a few words to you five who had ſubſcribed that book; that upon the conſideration of the many lying ſlanders there caſt upon us, ſome gathered by falſe reports, and ſome out of books, which books did witneſs ſo plainly againſt you, both to you, and to all that have read them, that if it might have been the will of God, any of you might have ſearched your conſcience (by that light which would teach you to do as you would be done by) and have come to repent, and found mercy: for ſo I thought, that perhaps ſome of them may be drawn to believe lyes through report, that when they ſee them laid open, will not perſiſt in it: for ſo was my heart in love to you, if there had been but any innocency in any of you, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat it might have been awakened to have pleaded againſt the deceit, and led you out of it; which was and is my deſire. But ſince you are the ſame, yea worſe, (according to that Scripture, <hi>Evil men and ſeducers grow worſe and worſe)</hi> wherefore I leave you to the righteous Judge of all cauſes; and for the ſake of the ſimple, (who elſe may come to be deceived by your ſubtilties and ſlanders) proceed to lay open ſome of your deceits in plain words, as God ſhall move.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:114714:3"/>
            <head>A Diſcovery of the Man of Sin, Acting in a Myſtery of Iniquity.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Nd firſt, a few words to your boaſtings, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you would make me vile and contemptible, and glory much in what you have done, as though you were the only men, and had o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verturned all before you: <hi>To which I anſwer,</hi> You might have ſpared your great boaſtings of your ſelves, (if your pride would have ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered you) and have left it to the Judgment of thoſe, who are guided by a ſpirit of Judgment, both yours and mine, to have been judged of: for it is not your great ſwelling words that can overturne the truth, but you muſt appear to be <hi>proud boaſters</hi> that the Scripture, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 30. 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 2. <hi>Jam</hi> 4. 16. may be fulfilled upon you in this, as it is in other marks left in Scripture, by which thoſe of your generation have been known, and are at this day.</p>
            <p>1. You charge me, <hi>That I have not ſufficiently anſwered your Book called, The Perfect Phariſee.</hi> To which I anſwer, That which mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved me to write what I did in anſwer to the ſlanders in it, was not to ſatisfie your wils, nor wiſdom, nor any who ſtand in their own wils or wiſdom for then had I become a man-pleaſer, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1. 10. and ſhould have forſaken the direction of the ſpirit of God, which did never in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny age ſerve and ſeed the ſerpents wiſdom; but what it ſpoke was foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhneſs and a myſtery to the wiſdom of the world; and it is the ſame at this day: But that which moved me, was for the ſimple ones ſake, leſt he ſhould come to be deceived by the ſleights of your ſlanders, and by the envious ſerpent: And I know and am aſſured, it hath and ſhal ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh the end for which it was ſent forth, and ſhall not returne in vain but ſhall be a ſavor of life unto ſome, according to his purpoſe by whom it was ſent forth: for it was not my own, nor in my own will and wiſdome: and though you would make the people beleeve it is not anſwered, that ſo you might glory in your ſelves, and provoke others to glory in you alſo; yet any that is wiſe may ſee, that what your envy
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:114714:4"/>
hath caſt upon us, in your 17. particulars. That which we hold and practiſe, is owned and proved by Scripture, and that which is falſe is denied in plainneſs of ſpeech without deceit: but to follow you in your janglings and wreſtings of Scripture, wherein you bring one Scripture to croſs another, (as is plain in your Book) and ſo walke unprofitably, was not my way, but rather to edification, for your confuſion is plain to any ſpiritual eye, and I need not add to it, nor do I delight in ſuch things, further then for the truths ſake I am moved, for the day is come that all ſhall be manifeſt, and you cannot be hid.</p>
            <p>Secondly, You accuſe me for groſly perverting the Scripture: <hi>to which I anſwer,</hi> I ſuppoſe the Reader will not finde any private in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation by me put upon any Scripture, but quoted as they are, without adding any ſenſe to them, but leaves them to the Reader to view; now whether I pervert them, who quotes them as they are in plain words as they are ſet down, or you who give your private mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings on them, and brings one to oppoſe and croſs another, and who perverts the Scripture, is plain to any who are guided by the ſame Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit who gave them forth, and I leave it to ſuch to judge.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, You accuſe me with <hi>palpable ſhufflings:</hi> to which I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, Shuffling and deceit I abhorre, and love and practiſe plainneſs and truth, and that is your advantage you have againſt us; as all your forefathers the perſecutors ever had againſt Chriſt and his Saints, who when they could not condemn them by any witneſs without them, yet they would aske them many queſtions to enſnare them; for the ſubtil ſerpent knows that they who are of the ſpiritual Seed, dare not deny that before men, which they own before God, though they ſuffer for it: and I know I ſhall not be accuſed as ſhuffling in my anſwer; by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny but thoſe of your Generation; and in my Conſcience I am cleared of it in the ſight of God, and ſo your ſlanders toucheth me not, but ſhal be your own garments to wear.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, You accuſe me of <hi>miſerable weakneſs,</hi> and you ſay, <hi>you cannot but ſmile at it, and may laugh at my ignorance:</hi> to which I anſwer, Herein you declare to all men, what Spirit you are of, who glory in your own ſtrength, and laugh at the weakneſs of others, which none that ever was guided by the Spirit of Chriſt ever did; but laugh on a while, yet know, your woe is coming, and your laughter ſhall be turned into weeping and howling: and for my weakneſs, (as you call it, where is my ſtrength) and ignorance, at which you ſo much rejoyce; if the ſtrength and wiſdom of God be but made perfect in it, that is it
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:114714:4"/>
I wait for, and herein ſhall the Scriptures be fulfilled, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 27. that <hi>God hath choſen the weake and fooliſh things to confound the mighty and wiſe:</hi> take notice of it betimes, you ſturdy oakes, and tall cedars, and tremble ye mountains at his preſence.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, You accuſe me with <hi>horrible rayling:</hi> To which I anſwer, What language have I uſed againſt you, except ſuch as the Spirit of God in Scriptures gives to thoſe of your generation? if I have not the language of the ſame Spirit, why doe you not mention it in particular, but ſo often accuſe in general, to render me odious? but deceit is got in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſuch fine colours, that it cannot beare a plaine language, for the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel would not be diſcovered and plainly dealt with, where he is, and therefore he hath bred up his children in manners, that they muſt not call him that vents his lyes a lyar; nor him whom he hath deceived and ſent out deceive others, a deceiver; nor one who takes hire, a hireling, though they be found in the very act; but ſome finer words muſt be u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; and here you that cannot beare the Scripture language, but cals it rayling, ſhews to all, what brood you are of, who would not be plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dealt with: but who is guided by the Spirit of God, is taught not to flatter, but to uſe plainneſs of ſpeech, yet not in envy; and whoſoever is free from opinion, and reads over both our writings, may eaſily finde out raylers, ſcorners, lyars, ſlanderers, and falſe accuſers: and let ſuch judge.</p>
            <p>And now a few words to the reſt of your ſlanders in particular: as for that you call a ſhort draught of my anſwer, I ſhall not ſay any thing to it here, being the many lyes that are in it, are ſo plainly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered to all who have read my anſwer, and will more fully be layd open hereafter when we come to the particulars.</p>
            <p>The firſt ſlander is grounded upon my ſubſcribing my ſelf, one whom the world cals <hi>James Nayler,</hi> and you ſay you are jealous of a myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Iniquitie from theſe words; and though you confeſs the ground to be your own jealouſie, yet you proceed to ſlander upon it; and tels where the myſterie lyes, and this you ſay is to cloake our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of being equal with God, and that we herein depart from Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and would conclude God and Chriſt under carnal obſervations, or elſe teach them to ſpeak. To which I anſwer, How any whom theſe men love not, can be free from their aſperſions, let any man judge; who can ſo highly ſlander upon the ground of their own jealouſie; and how this jealouſie is grounded, any may judge: For firſt, are not the words true? am not I one whom the world cals <hi>James Nayler?</hi> and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:114714:5"/>
they know no other name, and yet the Scripture ſpeaks (<hi>Rev.</hi> 2. 17.) of <hi>him that overcometh,</hi> having <hi>a new Name, that no man knows but he that hath it;</hi> and how do we here depart from Scripture? nay<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> who witneſs the new man eſtabliſh the Scripture, and witneſs the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of Chriſt fulfilled in him: and here I charge you in the preſence of the living God, to be coatrary to the Scriptures, and the Spirit that gave them forth, and with it ſhall be judged eternally; and that new name you know not, as you make it appear; and how we exclude God and Chriſt under carnal obſervations, or teach them to ſpeak in owning the promiſe fulfilled: and if this be not a moſt wicked and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſlander caſt upon us, to make us odious, let the Reader judge.</p>
            <p>And you would have the people beleeve that the man of ſin is to be found at <hi>Rome,</hi> that ſo they may not diſcover him neerer hand in your ſelves: but they who obſerve your practiſe, preaching <hi>loe here,</hi> and <hi>loe there,</hi> and printing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for the upholding of the kingdom of ſin, making people beleeve they ſhall never be free from it, while they are on the earth: they where the Spirit of Chriſt is doth diſcover the man of ſin neerer hand; for whoever oppoſeth the end of Chriſts coming<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which was to take away ſin and to ſet free from it, and to preſent perfect un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Father without ſpot or blemiſh, ſuch are Antichriſts, and the man of ſin acts in them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to uphold his own kingdom, which is ſin: and there you are, as your practiſe, printing, and preaching, may witneſs; and are diſcovered by the Spirit of Chriſt where it is, though you have long acted in a myſterie, for are not you the ſame men who have had great ſums of mony for crying out againſt ſin? but now that the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of ſin begins to fall<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> you have changed your voyce, and tels peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple they muſt never be free from ſin while they live, nor ever attain to perfection, and ſo takes peoples money for pleading againſt the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of Chriſt, who ſaith <hi>Be ye perfect even as your heavenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is perfect,</hi> Mat. 5. 48. <hi>Be ye holy, for I am holy</hi> 1 Pet. 1. 15. 16. Eph. 5. 27. and ſo being found to miniſter againſt Chriſt, he is blinde who cannot ſee you to be miniſters of Antichriſt for they who were miniſters of Jeſus Chriſt prayed and preached <hi>for the perfecting of the Saints, that they might perfect what was lacking in their faith</hi> 1 Theſ. 3. 10. <hi>that they might preſent every one perfect in Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> Col. 1. 28. and bring up to perfection, <hi>even to the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure ſtature, and fulneſs of Chriſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> Eph. 4. 12. and ſuch ſaid, <hi>how can you that are dead to ſin, live any longer therein? Rom.</hi> 6. which you deny, that any can attain to perfection or freedom from
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:114714:5"/>
ſin, while they are here, and ſo are acted by a contrary Spirit to Chriſt and all that ever he ſent forth, and would make people beleeve, that Chriſt had commanded that which none ſhould ever attain to: and thoſe who witneſs it, and would preſs others to preſs after it, in the power of Chriſt, ſuch you reckon up among thoſe you call blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, and heretical doctrine: but all this is, that you may be made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt whoſe miniſters you are.</p>
            <p>And whereas you reckon us up among the Papiſts, thereby to make us odious unto people, but are you not aſhamed of it, who are found amongſt them your ſelves in many things which you call your wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip? wherein we deny both them and you; and they are one with you againſt us, in perſecution and revilings: have not they builded the Idols Temples, and you worſhip in them? are not you one with them in obſerving many dayes, and times, and forms: as ſprinkling infants, ſinging, and many ſuch like things? are you not one with them, in bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring rule as lords and maſters over the Common People, and would have to doe in ordering of the State-affairs? are you not one with them, as in your tythes and fat parſonages, and divers other things which might be mentioned? all which we deny yours and their practiſe as being contrary to the Saints in Scripture, and commands of Chriſt. And where is there one Papiſt ownes us? I command you all, (<hi>you Prieſts</hi>) to make your ſlander good, or elſe lay your hands on your mouths in ſilence<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and confeſs your ſelves to all the world to be lyars.</p>
            <p>And now to the particulars wherein you charge us to be one with the Papiſts: I charge you to be lyars, and do anſwer<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> As we receive not the ground of what we practiſe from the Papiſts or you; neither do we deny what is truth, becauſe they or you may profeſs it, but ſhall owne it before all the world, though by you we be reproached for it.</p>
            <p>And firſt, You charge us <hi>with denying Juſtification without us, and for witneſſing juſtification by Chriſt alone in us<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> which we owne, Chriſt in us, according to the meaſure made manifeſt: our ſanctification, juſtification, redemption from ſin, and the hope of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, <hi>Col.</hi> 1. 26, 27. and this we owne within us which is a myſtery, and hath been hid from ages, and is now hid from you and the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the world, as you make it appear. And here he th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t ſits in Heaven may have you in deriſion, and you to be ignorant of the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, who have ſhewed forth your folly.</p>
            <p>For the ſecond, You charge us, <hi>for being juſtified by inherent
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:114714:6"/>
righteouſneſs:</hi> which word we deny; it is a word of your own coyning: but by being <hi>made the righteouſneſs of God in Chriſt,</hi> (2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 21.) and denying all our own righteouſneſs, are we juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied. And this Chriſt and this righteouſneſs we witneſs within us in meaſure.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, you charge upon us that we ſay, <hi>Every Saint is perfect<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> and <hi>that it is poſſible to be perfectly holy, and without ſin, and yeeld perfect obedience to the Law of God.</hi> I anſwer: To your firſt, it is a lying ſlander, that we ſay every Saint is perfect: for we witneſs the Saints growth, and the time of preſſing after-perfection. To your ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond: we own it, that it is poſſible to be perfectly holy and without ſin: and herein we have the Saints in Scripture to witneſs with us; which I charge you to be ignorant of, and not come to the firſt prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples: who witneſſed the new birth, freedom from ſin, and perfection. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 14. As to your third, I anſwer, that <hi>not one jot or tittle of the Law ſhall paſs, till all be fulfilled:</hi> and it was the end for which God ſent his Son manifeſt in the fleſh, that by him <hi>the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of the Law might be fulfilled in us, who walk not after the fleſh, but after the Spirit,</hi> Rom. 8. 3, 4. And herein we have the Saints in Scripture to witneſs with us. The fourth thing which you charge upon us<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> is, <hi>That the Spirit is not to be tried by Scripture.</hi> To which I anſwer: That Spirit which is of God, is one with that which gave forth the Scripture, where-ever it is: yet can none who have not that Spirit, try the ſpirits by the Scripture: for they who have not that infallible ſpirit that gave forth the Scriptures, have the ſpirit of Errour, and judge amiſs both of Spirit and Scripture, as the Scribes and Phariſees did, and you do. But they who have that infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible ſpirit which gave forth the Scripture, have that which tryed the ſpirits before the Scripture was: and ſuch have their touchſtone wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in them, and not without them; and ſuch need not go to the letter to try the ſpirits. The fifth thing you charge upon us<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> is, to <hi>cry down the neceſſity of the written Word and call it a dead letter, and that it is but a declaration of them that ſpoke it forth.</hi> To which I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer: Where read you of a written Word? But if you thereby mean the Scriptures, which we call a declaration of them that ſpake them forth; It is true, we do ſo; and they who ſpake them forth, witneſs them with us to be a declaration, (<hi>Luke 1. 1. 1 Joh.</hi> 1. 3.) and the letter, and not the ſpirit. But that we cry down the neceſſity of the Scriptures, is falſe: for they are our own, and we ſee them of uſe
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:114714:6"/>
every day, in bearing witneſs with us againſt you and your Heatheniſh Worſhips, and unſanctified lives, who are <hi>belly-gods, evil beaſts.</hi> And for you that ſay the four books are the Goſpel, make it appear: you never knew him who is the glad things<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which Goſpel was manifeſt before theſe books were written, and is <hi>everlaſting.</hi> Sixthly, you charge upon us <hi>the owning of an immediate call, and the Word of the Lord coming to us.</hi> To which I anſwer: Let all the Prophets and Apoſtles, and holy men of God in the Scripture, witneſs againſt you; who all owned the immediate call, and the Word of the Lord; and be you witneſſes againſt your ſelves, that you never had the Word of the Lord coming unto you, but are of thoſe who ſay, <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord when the Lord never ſpoke unto you, (Jerem.</hi> 23. from verſ. 21. to 33.) but are lyers and falſe Prophets by your own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, who reckon it up as a blaſphemous doctrine, to witneſs the Word of the Lord coming unto us: and be alſo witneſſes againſt your ſelves, who deny an immediate call, that you never were called of God: for his call is immediate, whereby he hath called his, and ſent them forth: which call I witneſs from the mouth of the Lord. But you are of thoſe who run unſent, and therefore do not profit the people; whoſe call is mediate, and ſo never any was called by God, and ſo are made Miniſters <hi>by the will of man.</hi> And as your Call is carnal and medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſo is your Miniſtery, who have not the Word of the Lord, but what you ſteal from your neighbour, out of a book; which none of the true Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>phets of the Lord ever did; and ſo out of your own mouth be ye judged, and diſcovered to all the children of light to be in the errour. Seventhly, you charge us with <hi>putting abundance of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs in faſting, beggerly apparel, wandering up and down the world.</hi> To which I anſwer: Our holineſs is in Chriſt. But you that ſcorn faſting, and wandering up and down<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſcorn that which the holy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> men of God ever owned. <hi>Heb</hi> 11. 37, 38. Chriſt faſted, and the Prophets and Apoſtles were in faſtings often. Chriſt wandered up and down and had not whereon to lay his head: and many followed him. And the Apoſtles wandered to and fro, and had <hi>no certain dwelling place<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> 1 Cor. 4. 11. Now had you lived in their days you would have reproached them, as you do thoſe that follow them now: and ſo here I charge you to be acted by a contrary ſpirit to Chriſt, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Apoſtles. And for <hi>beggerly apparel:</hi> you that reproach us becauſe that we have caſt off needleſs pride and exceſs, (for no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther beggerly apparel do I know uſed amongſt us) you would have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:114714:7"/>
thoſe who wandered up and dow in ſheeps skins and goats skins, lodged in dens and caves of the earth: for ſuch were hated by your generation then, as we are now. And now let all judge by what ſpirit you are acted, who would make the world believe theſe were the fruits of the man of ſin, and the myſtery of the Babyloniſh iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. And for your ſmiling at my weakneſs, in ſaying that <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog</hi> are gathered together againſt Chriſt and his<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> kingdom, which you would put far off from your ſelves to the Turks and Saracens, at the converſion of the Jews: I tell you, The Jews are converting, and you are of thoſe Heathens who are banding together againſt Chriſt, with <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog;</hi> who is king of the Jews, and you are diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to be enemies unto him: and the Trumpet is ſounded, and the Battel is begun; and your rage is great, with the reſt of the Heathen. But the Lamb muſt take the kingdom: bleſſed be our God for ever.</p>
            <p>And whereas you accuſe me for ſaying <hi>that you can ſcarcely agree among your ſelves in that which you call the worſhip of God:</hi> Have I ſpoken here any thing but truth? as they that know you may wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs with me; though you would put it off to matters of Diſcipline. And you accuſe <hi>A. P.</hi> to report it; which is falſe: and here I charge you Prieſts to miniſter lyes, and to ſlander him: for he hath not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported it to me. But it ſeems your conſciences accuſe you, and you would charge it upon him: but your practice reports it.</p>
            <p>And whereas you ſay <hi>this doth not make you like Herod and Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late:</hi> neither do I ſay that onely doth, but your joyning together in one againſt Chriſt and his kingdom, and your hatred againſt the truth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> therein you reſemble them.</p>
            <p>And whereas you bring <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> to warrant your diviſions; you may let their conditions alone: for few in the Nation live more unlike <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> then you: therefore go not about to make them like your ſelves, who live in pride and covetouſneſs, as Lords and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters over your hearers, ſuing or compelling them to pay you tythes or wages; running from place to place for more money, and call that your call to the Miniſtery, and deny the immediate call of Chriſt, and the word of the Lord coming to you; which the Apoſtles never did: therefore for ſhame never compare your ſelves to the Apoſtles, who are found amongſt the hirelings and falſe prophets.</p>
            <p>And whereas you would excuſe your ſelves from ſpeaking evil of our forſaking the world, and would cover it over with deceitful words; Let any that reads your words judge, if they be not ſpoken in reproach
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:114714:7"/>
to that our practice; who call it but <hi>a pretence:</hi> and our obedience in anſwering the call of Chriſt, in forſaking the world, this you call <hi>a ſinful neglect of our families.</hi> And do you not belye the Apoſtle, when you ſay he calls thoſe <hi>the rudiments of the world?</hi> And do not thoſe who forſake the world, forſake the pride and luſt of it, which you live in? And whereas you ſay it is a ſinful neglect of our fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, and you know it to be a ſin; and yet you ſay you ſpeak not againſt the world in its proper Goſpel-ſenſe: and you inſtance <hi>Fox</hi> and <hi>Nay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler</hi> as two evident examples of it.</p>
            <p>And you ſay <hi>We do ſinfully neglect our callings.</hi> To which I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer: Jeſus Chriſt having called us forth by his immediate voice, to leave all and follow him to do the work he hath for us to do. Whether obeying and coming forth, contrary to our own wills, taking up our Croſs and following him, or diſobeying, and abiding in our eſtates and pleaſures in the world; now in a Goſpel-ſenſe whether of theſe is a ſinful neglect of our callings, let the Scriptures of the Prophets and Apoſtles, and all the holy men of God judge, who have been called, and obeyed, and come forth; and condemn you and your ſlander who are ignorant of the call of Chriſt, and do oppoſe it in them who obey it, and call it ſinful: and you bring Scriptures to oppoſe it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which will fall upon your own backs. As for providing for our families, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. 8. they are provided for by him who provides for us; and they want nothing.</p>
            <p>And as for <hi>thoſe that do not work, that they ſhould not eat;</hi> and <hi>thoſe who live diſorderly, not working at all,</hi> 1 Theſſ. 3. 10. 11. how are you not aſhamed to take theſe Scriptures into your mouthes, when all that know you may witneſs this againſt you, that no ſort of people in the Nation lives like you for idleneſs, like beaſts and ſwine: for 1. Your families are provided for by the ſweat of other mens brows. 2. You are thoſe that walk diſorderly not working at all<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and therefore ought not to eat. 3. And for abiding in our callings, we are in them, and there abide with God: but you are crept in and are not called of God, by your own confeſſion, who never heard his voice.</p>
            <p>And whereas you make an Objection, leſt we ſhould ſay that the Apoſtles left their callings and followed Chriſt: and you ſay, <hi>'Tis true, the Meſſiah had his diſciples following him: but Paul after Chriſts aſcenſion left a ſtanding rule</hi> (ſay you) <hi>for all to abide in their cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings.</hi> As if when Chriſt ſhould ever call out any more, they ſhould not obey him; as though <hi>Paul</hi> had left a ſtanding rule to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:114714:8"/>
And thus you bring <hi>Paul</hi> to oppoſe the commands of Chriſt, and one Scripture to croſs another; and yet would not be counted wreſters of Scriptures, nor oppoſers of Chriſt. But you are found out, and can no longer be hid.</p>
            <p>And whereas you tell of them who were called forth, having an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate call, and to pub like work in the Miniſtery; herein, I ſay, ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence fleſh, who knows nothing of that immediate call to that publike work, but denies it.</p>
            <p>And whereas you tell of <hi>Paul</hi> reproving Chriſtians for leaving their callings: I anſwer: Did <hi>Paul</hi> reprove them for leaving all, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth at the commands of Chriſt? O with what ſubtilty do you go about here to make people believe that Chriſt ſhould never call out any more, not they obey!</p>
            <p>And whereas you tell, that a man may forſake the world, and yet enjoy his poſſeſſions in it: I anſwer: Such a forſaking of the world pleaſeth you well; and ſo do you forſake the world, when you leave one Parſonage, to go to a greater Living: and this is all the forſaking of the world that you know or can judge of. But did ever any that Chriſt called forth to be Miniſters, forſake the world ſo? but they left all at his command.</p>
            <p>And whereas you tell of <hi>uſing this world as not abuſing it,</hi> and many ſuch-like words, which you know nothing of: I anſwer: When you come to live in what you ſpeak, and ſo to uſe this world, you will ceaſe to compel your hearers to pay you Tythes or Money for your hours talk, or one to pull out another for greater Livings: for he who ſpoke thoſe words did no ſuch things; and till you come to live that life, you have nought to do with thoſe words.</p>
            <p>And whereas you ſay you ſpoke not a ſillable of the pride and luſts of the world, in your Epiſtle, but it is foiſted in by <hi>James Nayler:</hi> I anſwer: Doth not he that forſakes the world, forſake the pride and luſts of it? which you live in<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſeem to ſpeak evil of them that do forſake the world, as is plain in your book: and then what wrong have I done you? for I do not charge you with the words, but with the thing.</p>
            <p>And now for thoſe things you have ſet down as trivial obſervances, they are theſe; our <hi>not ſaluting;</hi> which we witneſs a command to the contrary: our <hi>not putting off the hat before the Magiſtrate;</hi> wherein we have the example of Chriſt and all the Apoſtles and Saints, and are plainly forbidden to <hi>have the faith of Chriſt in reſpect of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:114714:8"/>
perſons:</hi> and our <hi>Thouing every one;</hi> which is the Scriptures lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, and none of the holy men of God ever uſed any other to a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular: and our <hi>not calling men Maſters;</hi> which is the command of Chriſt in plain words. Now you that call your ſelves Miniſters, and call the commands of Chriſt <hi>trivial obſervances;</hi> I charge you in the preſence of the living God to be in the doctrine of devils, and there are ſeen by all the children of the light; and makes it plainly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, how little you regard the language of the Scriptures given out by the Spirit of God; or the practice of the Saints, who were guided by the ſame Spirit, or the expreſs commands of Jeſus Chriſt, but ſtand up to maintain the cuſtoms of the world, againſt all theſe: and here you plainly appear to whom you belong; for you who are guided by the ſpirit of the world, ſtand up to maintain the cuſtoms of the world; and they that are guided by the Spirit of God, are led into the ſame way, words, worſhip, and obedience, that thoſe walked in who were guided by the ſame Spirit before them: and none can live in the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Chriſt and conform to the cuſtoms of the world: neither doth the Apoſtle ſpeak of any of theſe, when he ſaith, <hi>Touch not, taſte not, handle not,</hi> as you would make people believe; but of your carnal Ordinances. And whereas you ſay we place Holineſs and Religion in theſe things; It is falſe; our holineſs is in Chriſt: but theſe things we cannot neglect, being the commands of Chriſt to us, and practice of the Saints in Scripture.</p>
            <p>And whereas you ſay we will not ſubmit to Chriſts righteouſneſs, I charge you to be lyers and ſlanderers: and that we alſo deny many other truths, with full oppoſition to Goſpel Ordinances, Prayer, Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſm, Supper, Church-Government and Miniſtery; which is all falſe, and a lying ſlander: for the righteouſneſs of Chriſt we own, and in him alone are we made <hi>the righteouſneſs of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> 1 Cor. 5. 21. But your righteouſneſs which live in ſin, and talk of righteouſneſs without you, and are not made conformable to Chriſt, but are conformable to the world, that righteouſneſs we deny. And Chriſt the Goſpel-Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance we own, and deny your carnal Ordinances, and ſet Forms. And Prayer we own, which is with the Spirit; and as the Spirit helps our infirmities, ſo we ask and receive of the Father: and deny the vain bablings of you Heathen, and you that <hi>under pretence make long prayers.</hi> And the Supper of the Lord we own, which is ſpiritual; and deny your carnal Sacrament, for which there is no Scripture; and your mixt multitudes. The Baptiſm of Chriſt we own, and are bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:114714:9"/>
               <hi>by one Spirit into one body.</hi> And the Holy Ghoſt and the fire we own, and do witneſs, but deny your ſprinckling of Infants for which there is no Scripture. Church-government, we own<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and Jeſus Chriſt the head and governour of his Church, to whom we ſubmit, but deny your Claſſes, Aſſemblies, and Maſterſhips, by which you rule and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern in your own wils: &amp; the Miniſters we own, which is of Ieſus Chriſt and immediate call to it, and deny all whoſe call is mediate, and are made miniſters by the will of man: and here I charge you in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Lord, to be ſlanderers and falſe accuſers, who ſay we deny theſe things. And whereas you would deny that you perſecuted us, and would put it upon thoſe who are ſent to you from the Lord, to witneſs againſt your deceit<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as though they were the perſecutors: but whether thoſe whom the Lord ſent out to cry wo againſt the falſe prophets and hirelings, calling them greedy dumb dogs, blinde guides, and many ſuch like playn words, or they who cauſed them to be haled before Rulers, there accuſed them, caſt them into priſon, and put them to death: whether of theſe were the perſecutors then? the ſame are the perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors now, as ſome of us can witneſs, who have been haled before Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, and there vehemently accuſed, and caſt into priſon, and ſome ſtoned; and not a few of you who call your ſelves miniſters, have had a hand in it, and been the cauſe of it: and whereas you ſay, <hi>You have been hindred in the ſeed of the word;</hi> I anſwer, What word have you to ſow, who deny the word of the Lord coming to you? but your ſeed being ſtollen, makes a bad harveſt, and little fruit to be reaped: and whereas you tell of bringing our ſelves within the compaſs of the Law, for declaring our meſſage to you from the Lord, and that we ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer as evil doers; here take notice whoſe miniſters you are, who have had papiſts Law, that guarded the Jeſuites contrary to the Scripture, to defend you with, which the miniſters of Chriſt never had: and Chriſt &amp; all the Saints ſuffered as evil doers in the account of thoſe, who were protected by carnal Laws: &amp; whereas you ſay <hi>You are ſet for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation and defence of the Goſpel:</hi> I pray you who ſet you ſince you deny the immediate call of God, and ſo have ſet your ſelves, or are ſet by the will of man? and that the Goſpel ſhould be defended by perſecution, and perſecutors was never known.</p>
            <p>Now a few words to your reply to my anſwer; and firſt, to your firſt poſition: as touching your accuſing <hi>George Fox,</hi> that he ſaid, <hi>that he was equall with God:</hi> and you ſay, your proof is not at all
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:114714:9"/>
denied. I anſwer, That thoſe words were ſpoken, is not denied: but that they are the words of <hi>George Fox,</hi> is denied. And you uſe many words, and ſay I make a difference between <hi>George Fox</hi> and himſelf; ſo that though <hi>George Fox</hi> is not equal with God, yet he that is called <hi>George Fox</hi> is equal with God. And thus when you have made up a piece of deceit to blinde the people, then you go about to frame an anſwer to confute it: and ſo you confute your own deceit, and not my words. For the ſum of mine anſwer was this, <hi>That George Fox was denied as duſt; but the Spirit that ſpoke in him is equal with God:</hi> according to the Scripture, and the words of Chriſt, who ſaith, <hi>When you are called before Rulers for my Names ſake, take no thought what to ſpeak: for it is not you that ſpeak, but the Spirit of your Father which ſpeaketh in you.</hi> Matth. 10. 20. Now <hi>George Fox</hi> being called before Rulers for the Name of Chriſt, he denies <hi>George Fox</hi> to ſpeak, and the creature who is but duſt, and wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth the Spirit of the Father ſpeaking in him, (though the words paſs through <hi>George Fox</hi>) and the words of Chriſt fulfilled. And are not the Father, and the Son, and the Spirit equal, where-ever they are? and muſt they not be ſuffered to ſpeak where they are? But you that are carnal know not the voice.</p>
            <p>Thus the anſwer is plain to any ſpiritual eye: but to ſatisfie you who cavil on purpoſe, is impoſſible: but what I ſay is for the ſimple ones ſake. And I ſhall not follow you in your arguments: for I know they ſhall deceive none but ſuch as are deceived already, and are willing ſo to be.</p>
            <p>Now whereas you ſay <hi>I blaſphemouſly abuſe the Scriptures;</hi> are you not aſhamed to charge me with the abuſing of them, who do but onely ſet them down as they are<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> without giving any meaning to them? which Scriptures you take, and wreſt them to another end then for which the holy Ghoſt ſpake them forth, adding your own invention &amp; words which the Scripture ſpeaks not. For where doth the Scripture ſpeak of <hi>a Phyſical or relative oneneſs?</hi> But by theſe words you darken knowledge, and blinde peoples mindes, leſt they ſhould ſeek after an oneneſs with God: for the Scripture faith<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>He that is joyned to the Lord, is one ſpirit,</hi> 1 Cor. 6. 17. and Chriſt ſaith, <hi>That they may be one, even as thou Father and I are one,</hi> Joh. 17. 21, 22, 23. and, <hi>As he is, ſo are we in this preſent world,</hi> 1 Joh. 4. 17. Which Scriptures you wreſt to another end, by your ſubril words ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to them. Now who blaſpemes the Scriptures, whether you or I, let truth judge, and your accuſation fall upon your own pate.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:114714:10"/>And for your falſly accuſing me to ſay <hi>I was as holy, juſt, and good as God himſelf;</hi> what I have ſaid in mine anſwer in my former book, may ſufficiently convince any one that fears God that I am clear of it. And whereas you bring <hi>William Baldwinſon</hi>'s teſtimony which may give evidence againſt your ſelves, and ſhew it to any honeſt heart, both your deceit and his. For before, I was charged with this in particular, and now you ſay <hi>Richard Farnworth</hi> and I both ſaid it; and he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed there was a great deal of people in the houſe. Now it was ſtrange we ſhould both ſay it, and none hear it but himſelf: for the great deal of people he ſpeaks of, they do witneſs againſt him in it, and divers of them have offered their teſtimony againſt him. But fending and proving becometh not Saints; nor did they ever uſe it: nor dare I ſtand by the witneſs of men, but have the witneſs of God againſt you and your ſlanders, <hi>who will reward every one according to their doings,</hi> both the ſlanderer and the lyer: and not onely by your reporting theſe, but alſo your ſeeking evidence to back them, herein you are ſerving the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil the father of lyes, and ſo make that appear to be true which I have ſpoken of you.</p>
            <p>Now for your charging <hi>George Fox</hi> to ſay he was <hi>the judge of the world,</hi> and you ſay I deny it not, but tell you that you are groſly igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of Chriſt: I anſwer, If you be not groſly ignorant of Chriſt and the Scripture, let any wiſe man judge: for you ſay, <hi>God hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted all judgement to the Son,</hi> and yet you will not own him to be judge where he is: wherein you go about either to exclude him from being in the Saints, and ſo would limit him into a particular place; or from being judge in them where he is. Now that you are ignorant of Chriſt, all that know him ſhall witneſs: for all that know him, know him in them, and that he judgeth the world in them, and the things of the world in every particular: and he that is judge of the world in particular, he is judge of the world in general; for he is but one in all the Saints, who is Judge, and ſhall be at the great day: which judgements you are ignorant of, who are carnal, and compare it with carnal judging of Juſtice at the Bench, and ſo compare ſpiritual things with carnal, and ſo appear to be ignorant of ſpiritual things, and that <hi>ſpiritual man</hi> which <hi>judgeth all things, yet he himſelf is judged of no man;</hi> which ſpiritual man being in <hi>George Fox,</hi> is judge of the world; but <hi>George Fox</hi> is denied: for we look not upon the viſible, but the inviſible, which is the Son of God. And this may ſerve for an anſwer to your reply, and for condemnation.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:114714:10"/>To the calling <hi>George Fox</hi> the Son of God; you know nothing of the Son of God as he was revealed in the Apoſtles, but are <hi>without God in the world,</hi> a neſt of Serpents. This Son is the ſame who is the Judge of the world. And whereas you ſpeak of the Angels not being this Son of God; It is true, <hi>he takes not upon him the nature of angels, but the ſeed of Abraham:</hi> and who ſeeth by this eye, judgeth the <hi>deep things of God,</hi> and <hi>ſearcheth the hearts,</hi> according to that meaſure as he is born up.</p>
            <p>And whereas you charge me with ſaying to one of you, <hi>How ſhould God reveal any thing to him, and I not know it?</hi> I anſwer: <hi>William Cole</hi> meeting me in the way, ſaid, <hi>He had a meſſage to me from the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, but that was not a convenient place:</hi> and here <hi>Cole</hi>'s ſpirit is tryed. I told him, <hi>Jeſus Chriſt was no reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter of places:</hi> and therein I diſowned him and his meſſage and ſaw it to be deceit. Whereupon I told him to this purpoſe: <hi>If Jeſus Chriſt ſhould have ſent him with any meſſage to me, I ſhould have owned it: for where the Spirit of Jeſus Chriſt is, that owns the meſſage of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And whereas you ſpeak of <hi>vindicating the honour of our dread Lord, and his Son Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> I anſwer: By your lying ſlanders of the innocent, you ſhall never vindicate his honour; for he is ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured by the truth: but herein you honour the devil, and do his work.</p>
            <p>And here <hi>Cole</hi>'s ſpirit is tried not to be the ſpirit of Chriſt, which reſpects places; and his meſſage to be a lye.</p>
            <p>For your Reply to the ſecond Poſition, <hi>That there is no diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of perſons in the Godhead:</hi> Before, you ſaid it was in <hi>Saul</hi>'s <hi>Errand,</hi> pag. 12. and now you ſay you did but infer it from thoſe words that <hi>George Fox</hi> ſaid, that <hi>it was but a buſie minde.</hi> But what ſhuffling is this? Are not you aſhamed to charge me with ſhuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fling, and are found in it your ſelves? What is it that you may not charge upon us by theſe falſe inferences? And when you are plainly told of it, you call it <hi>rayling.</hi> But your folly is made manifeſt to all men, and the ground you go upon, who ſlander by your falſe inferen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and gathered up reports from the mouthes of others, and give them out for truths. Here I charge you Prieſts to be ſlanderers and lyers.</p>
            <p>Now for your Reply to the third Poſition, <hi>That the ſoul is a part of the Divine eſſence:</hi> and you ſay I do not in the leaſt deny it: I anſwer to your charge: As to the general, I deny; and whether any ſpoke it in particular, or no, I queſtion; there being ſo many lyes char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:114714:11"/>
upon us from his mouth who affirms this: and how ſhall I either deny or confeſs it, unleſs I know the truth of it? And if any word in weakneſs be ſpoken by one<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> is this an honeſt ground you go upon, to charge it upon the whole in general? If any ſhould gather up the prophane words and walkings of many in your Pariſh, and charge them upon you, would not you think your ſelves wronged? And herein you appear to all, not to do as you would be done by. And for what is ſaid of our not knowing what the ſoul is: The endleſs diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes that are amongſt you concerning the ſoul of man, and what it is, ſhall witneſs againſt you, and with me, before all men, that I have done you no wrong, and that you are ignorant of the living ſoul.</p>
            <p>Poſit. 4. <hi>That Chriſt is in every man, and in the reprobate held under corruption:</hi> and in your Reply you ſay, I charge you with ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſlanders, and yet confeſs the thing. I anſwer, That Jeſus Chriſt is all, and in all, the light of the world, and <hi>lightneth every one that cometh into the world,</hi> without exception, is confeſſed: but that I ſaid, <hi>in the reprobate he is held under corruption</hi> which one of you ſaid you received from me in conference, that is denied. And here you adde lyes to ſlander withal; and what I ſaid of you is true, ſpoken not in envie, nor from the fulneſs of my gall, as you would make people be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, but in plainneſs and truth. And now you would ſhuffle it off to <hi>John Audland,</hi> becauſe he wrote in a letter to one that was fallen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from the Truth which he had once received, <hi>That ſuch crucified Chriſt within them afreſh,</hi> (according to the Scripture.) But is this to ſay that Chriſt in a reprobate is holden under corruption? let any judge. And thus you ſeem to go about to make amends for wronging of me, by caſting the ſame ſlander faſly upon another. But it ſeems you have a purpoſe to ſlander, and ſome muſt bear it.</p>
            <p>And for that expreſſion you ſay I uſed in <hi>Edward Briggs</hi> houſe; I deny it, and witneſs it to be no truer then the reſt, and from the ſame root. And for the Diſpute you ſpeak of at <hi>Pierce</hi>-bride, and <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſon</hi> whom you bring to prove your lyes, which you caſt upon me and others of my brethren who were at <hi>Pierce</hi>-bridge, <hi>Decemb.</hi> 12, where Prieſt <hi>Sanderſon</hi> came in, and many rude people with him; and ſaid that God had not given to every man a meaſure to profit withal. <hi>C. A.</hi> ſaid, Here is not one here which can deny but that Chriſt hath enlightned them; which light is the meaſure of God: which <hi>Sanderſon</hi> denied. But that any there ſaid that Chriſt in ſome was held under corruption, they that were there may all witneſs againſt
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:114714:11"/>
him. Therefore be aſhamed, inventers of lyes, who ſeck others to invent them alſo, and are lyars, who ſay Chriſt is a true light, but not the true light, as <hi>Saunderſon</hi> did there; and that Chriſt rules in all to whom he is given for a light, which is falſe: and here I charge you all<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Saunderſon</hi> &amp; the reſt, to be no miniſters of Chriſt who ſtumble at the light: for many ſay, we will not have this man to rule over us, <hi>and ſo deny the light, and the Lord that bought them;</hi> and this is the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, that light is come into the world, and ſuch abide in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and comprehend not the light, though the light ſhine in darkneſs: and here are you, who deny Chriſt to enlighten every one that cometh into the world, and to be in all, when the Scripture ſaith, <hi>There is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Greek nor Jew, circumciſion nor uncircumciſion, Barbarian, Scythian, bond nor free but Chriſt is all, and in all.</hi> Col. 3. 11. which Scripture doth plainly witneſs againſt you, though you deny it to your ſhame, who would reaſon againſt the infiniteneſs of Chriſt, who filleth Heaven and Earth: and here I charge you to be ignorant of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and blinde guides.</p>
            <p>And you undertake to open that place, <hi>John</hi> 1. 9. <hi>In the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning was the Word; all things were made by him;</hi> and in your ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of it, you ſay this was not Chriſt, nor a knowledge of Chriſt as Mediator, nor a light ſufficient to bring to ſalvation, when <hi>John</hi> ſaith, he came to bear witneſs to that light, <hi>and that Word became fleſh and dwelt amongſt us: and in him was life, and the life was the light of men; and this was the true light that inlightneth every one that cometh into the world: and we ſaw his glory, as the glory of the onely begotten Son of God, full of grace and truth: and</hi> John <hi>bare witneſs of him, ſaying<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> This is he of whom I ſpake<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> He that cometh after me is preferred before me;</hi> and this you deny to be Chriſt, nor a knowledge of Chriſt, nor a light ſufficient to ſalvation<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but call it a created light: and here you are witneſſes againſt <hi>John</hi> and what he witneſſeth of Chriſt, and the ſufficiency of the light of Chriſt to ſalvation; and this is your opening of the Scriptures; whereof all that read that Chapter of <hi>John</hi> may witneſs againſt you, and your o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penings; but by ſuch openings as this, do you ſhut the kingdom of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, neither will enter in your ſelves, nor ſuffer them that would.</p>
            <p>And whereas you tell of <hi>James Naylers wicked blaſphemy, in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming that Chriſt as man dwels in him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer, That is falſe, and thoſe words were not ſpoken by me: for being asked, <hi>If Chriſt as man dwelt in me,</hi> my anſwer was, that
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:114714:12"/>
Chriſt I witneſs, who is God and man, which words you wreſt to ſlander withal, but ſpeake not the words as they came from me, and you make much a doe to prove, that a natural light is not the light of Chriſt, and thereby would make people beleeve, that that light ſpoken of in the 1 of <hi>Iohn</hi> is a natural light: but ſo plainly is your deceit layd open to any, who know any thing of Chriſt, that your arguments need no further anſwering: Only whereas you would prove in <hi>Mat.</hi> 13. 11. <hi>To you it is given to know the myſteries of the Kingdom of Heaven<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to them it is not given;</hi> there by you would inferre, that Chriſt doth not enlighten every man.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, The light of Chriſt hath its degrees and meaſures, ſo that though he be tendred a light to all, yet all doe not receive that light, nor walke in it, but deny it, and ſuch come not up to the knowledge of the myſteries of the Kingdom of Heaven: <hi>for only to them that recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved him, to them he gave power,</hi> ſo that denying the light<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> you deny the power, and abide in darkneſs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and are out of the fear of God, but the <hi>ſecret of the Lord is with them that fear him:</hi> and whereas you call that a naturall light which enlightneth every man which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth into the world: and <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith, <hi>This is the true light which en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightneth every one that cometh into the world;</hi> here you would make <hi>Iohn</hi> a lyar, and Chriſt who is the true light to be natural; and thus you wreſt the Scriptures to your own deſtruction, and all that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve you: and you ſay the Apoſtle 1 of <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 14. makes an oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion between naturall and ſpiritual light, and puts an impoſſibilitie of diſcovering Chriſt by the light of nature.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, You bely the Apoſtle<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and bewreſt his words, as you do ours, for the Apoſtle doth not ſpeak there of a naturall light and a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall light, for that which is naturall is darkneſs, neither have you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Scripture to prove that to be a natural light, which enlightens eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one that coms into the world, but ye children of darkneſs envy the light of Chriſt, and would make people beleeve its natural and carnal.</p>
            <p>And whereas you ſay, <hi>That that myſtery was hid from ages and generations;</hi> It is true, it was ſo but when Chriſt was manifeſt who was that light<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> then it was revealed both by <hi>Iohn</hi> and Chriſt himſelfe, ſaying, <hi>I am the light of the world he that followeth me ſhall not abide in darkneſs but ſhall have the light of life:</hi> and whereas you are quarrelling with <hi>A. P. A. P.</hi> may do it with authority, ſeeing you doe terme the light of Chriſt to be naturall, for denying your di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction of naturall and ſpiritual light, and you ſay the Lord Jeſus and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:114714:12"/>
the Apoſtles are full for it, yet have you not brought one Scripture to witneſs that light we ſpeake of to be a naturall light; but we have Chriſt and the Apoſtles witneſſing againſt you, it to be the light of Chriſt, ſo that we have the authority of the Scriptures, and yours is the novell opinions you ſpeak of: and for my ſaying <hi>that Chriſt muſt be in the vileſt of the world,</hi> to ſee the thoughts of the heart, and judge the inward part, or elſe how ſhall he judge righteous judgment upon every thought &amp; intent, which come not forth into action? &amp; this word which I ſpake of Chriſts being in the moſt vile, you change to dwell in: thus by deceit you change my words into your owne lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, and ſo go about to confute your own words<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but not mine<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as I ſpake them: though I do not ſay Chriſt dwels in Hell<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yet the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſaith, <hi>If I make by bed in Hell, thou art there.</hi> If you knew Chriſt, you would know him that ſaid ſo: Pſal. 139. 8. and here you prieſts ignorance is diſcovered. And here you ſay it is ridiculous to inferre that Chriſt dwels in all, becauſe he knows all things.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, For inferring and dwelling, they are your own words, but where he ſeeth any thing, there he is preſent, though you blinde creatures ſee him not, but they who know him know that he is infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite, and that he fils Heaven and Earth, and his preſence is the life of all Creatures, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1. 23. and here I charge you to be them that hate the light, and ſtumble.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Poſition</hi> 5. <hi>That Chriſt in the fleſh with all he did and ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red therein, was but a figure, and nothing but an example.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And theſe words you ſay are expreſly found in <hi>Sauls Errand<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> which I deny<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and bring that Book to be a witneſs againſt you, and that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull Spirit that acts in you; and for which you ſay, I pretend nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to Conſcience nor modeſty, that doth challenge you there with a lye: I anſwer, if thoſe words, <hi>that Chriſt with all he did was but a figure, and nothing but an example,</hi> be expreſly found in <hi>Sauls Errand<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> then you may ſay I have done you wrong, and I ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs it: but if theſe words be not expreſly found there, (as I know they are not) then all your ſhuffling will not cleare you; but the lye is found in your mouth; what I have ſayd of you will be found true, for it is one thing to ſay Chriſt is a figure, or example, and another thing to ſay, <hi>with all he did and ſuffered was but a figure, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but an example;</hi> and whereas you bring <hi>Iohn Iaques</hi> teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony to ſtrengthen your ſlander againſt me, that I ſhould write to <hi>Henry Holme,</hi> that if he expected to be ſaved by him that dyed at
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:114714:13"/>
Jeruſalem, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e was deceived: I anſwer, Many things are caſt upon us by words, and ſo by words muſt be proved or diſproved: but this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in a letter (as you ſay) why is not the letter produced? which was my deſire at the Seſſions, when I was accuſed, but none of you mine accuſers could produce any ſuch Letter; and I challenge <hi>John Jaques, Henry Holm,</hi> and you all, to produce ſuch a letter of my writing that hath thoſe words in it, or any thing in it, wherein <hi>that Chriſt which died at Jeruſalem is denied for ſalvation:</hi> and what was written to <hi>Henry Holm,</hi> I writ with my own hands, as divers that were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent can witneſs: and a copy of it was taken, which was afterwards delivered to the Juſtices, whereby they ſaw the envious ſlanders caſt upon me, to be falſe; now produce that letter that I wrote to <hi>Henry Holm:</hi> and here I command you, and charge you in the preſence of the living God, (<hi>you Prieſts</hi>) to bring forth that note, and it will clear me; which I know none of you dare, leſt you be found lyars.</p>
            <p>And whereas you challenge me to produce one Scripture, wherein Chriſt is called a figure: I anſwer, My words were, <hi>A figure</hi> or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample; which in my ſenſe are both one: wherein he ſhewed or figured out the way <hi>for Chriſtians to follow:</hi> and the word <hi>figure</hi> I ſpake not as from the Scripture, but in relation to <hi>Richard Hubbethornes</hi> letter, which if his own ſence may be taken of his words, he ſaith, <hi>A figure or an holding out in out ward actions among men thoſe things that he will truly ſpiritually, and really do in the ſpirits of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, at his ſecond coming:</hi> and theſe are witneſſed to be his words in <hi>William Mores</hi> letter: which ſence conſidered by any charitable Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, the word figure will not appear ſo hainous a crime as you would make it, though the word <hi>example</hi> I own to be the language of the Scriptures.</p>
            <p>Now for your 6. <hi>Poſition, That men are not juſtified by that righteouſneſs of Chriſt which he in his own perſon did fulfil with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out us:</hi> and you charge it upon us as hainous blaſphemy to witneſs Chriſt in us our juſtification; but what a juſtification is that of yours which is without, which is contrary to what the Saints witneſſed in the Scripture? for their juſtification was in the Spirit, and what is in the Spirit is within, and they witneſſed Chriſt in them, for ſanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, juſtification &amp; hope of glory: and Chriſt was in them, which diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them from reprobates; but your juſtification which is without you is in the outward man, at a diſtance: Chriſt is without you, and ſo
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:114714:13"/>
God ever witneſſed: and ye bring many Scriptures, but not one of them that ſpeaks of a juſtification without. That we are <hi>juſtified freely by his grace,</hi> we own: and that God hath ſet him forth to be a <hi>propitiation:</hi> that <hi>he was wounded for our tranſgreſſions:</hi> and that <hi>he laid on him the iniquities of us all,</hi> and his ſufferings we own: and we witneſs what he did, he doth ſtill in us, and bears and ſupports us, and ſo <hi>the remainders of the ſufferings of Chriſt that are yet behinde are</hi> by him <hi>fulfilled in us:</hi> and by his mighty work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in us, is the man of ſin caſt out. And this we witneſs the ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of Chriſt in us now bearing your reproaches and perſecution and impriſonments, and all the venom the Serpent can caſt upon him: and by his ſufferings ſhall he bruiſe that which is head in you, and all the perſecutors in the world. And this we witneſs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and deny your juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation which is without, which ſtands in words without power.</p>
            <p>Now to the ſeventh Poſition, <hi>That men are juſtified by that righteouſneſs which Chriſt within us enabled us to perform;</hi> or, which is in effect as ſome of them have expreſſed by <hi>inherent holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi> And you bring many proofs, that we ſay, <hi>The light in us will not onely diſcover ſin, but redeem from it, and bring to the fear of God, and ſo lead up to juſtification in the exerciſe of a pure con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience towards God and man.</hi> I anſwer: For the Poſition, as you have framed it up with your own words, of <hi>inherent holineſs,</hi> and the like, your words we deny: But that the light of Chriſt which we wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in us, is ſufficient to lead out of darkneſs, bring into the fear of God, and to exerciſe a pure conſcience before God and man in the power of Chriſt, this we witneſs, according to the words of Chriſt (who is our juſtification) and the Apoſtles; and yours to be contrary thereunto: <hi>Joh. 8. 12. I am the light of the world: he that follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth me ſhall not walk in darkneſs, but ſhall have the light of life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And whereas you charge me with ſaying, <hi>that no unperfect thing can be reconciled to God;</hi> and you would bring <hi>Paul</hi> for a proof, who ſaid <hi>he was carnal, and ſold under ſin;</hi> and <hi>what he would do that he did not:</hi> to this I anſwer: That in <hi>Paul</hi> which was car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, and ſold under ſin, which warred againſt the law of his minde, was not reconciled to God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but was for death: for where reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is, there is no more wars. And here you ſhew your blindeneſs. And you ſay <hi>Peter</hi> when he denied his Maſter was in a juſtified eſtate: which if he was, why did he <hi>weep bitterly</hi> and repent? But thus you blinde lead the blinde into the ditch<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> who ſay that one denying
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:114714:14"/>
Chriſt is in a ſtate of juſtification. But by whom is he juſtified who denies Chriſt? And becauſe I deny juſtification by our own works, and own him who worketh in us to will and to do, and herein deny ſelf-works<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> this you ſay is an old thred-bare ſhuffle of the Papiſts: by which it ſeems you diſown it, and would make it odious becauſe the Papiſts hold it. But the Truth we own for the truths ſake, neither becauſe the Papiſts own it, nor you deny it: for by him alone are we juſtified, and the witneſs is within us. Here let all the children of the light judge you with the light to be in your own works with the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, which have gotten the form of words, as you have, but both deny the power; and with the power of God we deny you both, and ſee the curſe upon you both.</p>
            <p>Now to your eighth Poſition, <hi>That God and man cannot be whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reconciled, till he be brought into the ſtate of the firſt Adam, and able in his own power to ſtand perfect.</hi> And you are offended that I ſhould ſay that the book ſhould witneſs againſt your falſe ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; and that the word is twice repeated, <hi>to ſtand in Gods power, and not in his own.</hi> I anſwer: I ſhall appeal to any ſober Chriſtian who reads the Querie, whether the words carry not the very ſame ſenſe twice over; where it is ſaid, <hi>Able in his power to have ſtood if they had not for ſaken his power, and conſented to the wiſdom of the ſerpent.</hi> Where if I had ſpoken of the power of man and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, then it ſhould have been ſet down <hi>their power,</hi> and not <hi>his power,</hi> which onely holds forth the power of God. And for your deceitful reaſoning to back your ſlander, wherein you would deny <hi>Adam</hi> in that ſtate of innocencie to ſtand in the power of God; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you ſhew you know not <hi>Adam</hi> in innocencie, nor his ſtanding with God: for while he ſtood, he ſtood in that power, and wiſdom, and counſel of God: and the looking out from that, was the cauſe of his fall. And here all that ever know <hi>Adam</hi> in innocencie ſhall witneſs againſt your ignorance and fooliſhneſs.</p>
            <p>And whereas you charge <hi>George Fox</hi> with ſcoffing at the grace of God; and that to pray for the ſight of ſin, and for power from ſin, is a tempting of God; and to pray for light to diſcover ſin, and refrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from it, are needleſs: I anſwer: This ſlander comes from the ſame root of the reſt. For ſcoffing at the grace of God, it is falſe: I charge you to be lyers, in the preſence of the living God, and you for eternal condemnation: for, the grace of God he owns, as is plain, where he ſaith, <hi>The free grace of God hath appeared to all men, which ſhews
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:114714:14"/>
ſin and evil; which whoſoever lives in, after it be diſcovered by the grace of God, and yet with a pretence makes a prayer to God to give them a ſight of their ſins, when God hath letten them ſee their ſins freely by his grace, and they will not forſake it: ſuch tempt God, and their prayers are abomination; and God will not hear the prayers of them that regard iniquity.</hi> But how falſly you gather from theſe words, that to pray for power againſt ſin, or to refrain from it, is to tempt God, or a thing needleſs, let any one that fears the Lord, judge, and witneſs againſt your ſlanderous ſpirit. But wickedneſs ſhall be upon the head of the wicked. And for the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and practice of the Saints, which was to overcome and forſake ſin, them we own, and have union with, in that which is holy; and they witneſs with us againſt your practice, who live in ſin, and plead for it, and for a pretence make long prayers. And for that you call <hi>Nay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler</hi>'s lyes, becauſe I ſay you are ſlanderers, which ſhall appear to be true more and more to all the children of light, under your own hands. And whereas you would go about to prove <hi>Adam</hi> in the ſtate of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocencie under the Covenant of Works, and that he had the Levitical Law (for that is the Covenant of Works) I anſwer: What were the works that he was to do for life? for the Covenant of Works ſaith, <hi>Do this, and live:</hi> but he had the life already, while he ſtood in it; and ſo it was not to be obtained by working: and the Scripture ſaith, <hi>The Law was added, becauſe of tranſgreſſion;</hi> which if it had been before the tranſgreſſion, could not have been. And <hi>Adam</hi> in his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocencie ſtood not by the Moral Law, as you call it: for that which was given to <hi>Adam</hi> was, <hi>Thou ſhalt not eat;</hi> which nowhere in Scripture is called<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the Covenant of Works. Thus while you laugh at my ignorance, as you ſay, you diſcover your own wickedneſs and folly.</p>
            <p>Now to your ninth Poſition, <hi>That no man that commits ſin, or that is not perfectly holy, can ever enter into the kingdom of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, unleſs there be a Purgatory.</hi> And in your Reply, you think ſtrange that I ſhould deny your wreſting of my words to another pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe then for which I ſpoke them. But ſeeing your charge is grounded upon my Querie, why have you altered the words from what I wrote? as by inſerting the word [<hi>ever</hi>] whenas he that hath ſinned may repent, and ſo his ſin be done away: and your adding the words [<hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nleſs there be a Purgatory</hi>] as though I owned a cleanſing after death. When as the Querie is, <hi>Whether you own a Purgatory or no, who ſay none</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:114714:15"/>
can be clean from ſin while they live. Now I ſhall appeal to any where there is honeſty, if you have not wreſted my words, and you in the Papiſts minde again in that Querie, whenas you charge me with owning a Purgatory, which I deny, as is plain by theſe words, (ſeeing the tree muſt lie as it falls) &amp; this is your deceit, which would perſwade the Reader to look upon my words, according to your falſe interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, when you have wreſted them, and not as I ſpake them; but when my words will not ſerve you to ground your ſlanders on, as they are ſet down, then you take and alter them for your own ends, and that this is not a ſhuffle, (and your ſhuffle I own not, which ſhall ſtand for your ſelves) but plain dealing in me, to clear the truth from your ſlanders, may appear to all, who read both our books.</p>
            <p>And whereas you ſay, <hi>You have found me out a medium, for the waſhing of the ſins of them that die in ſins, which is neither holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs here, nor a purgatory; but the blood of the Lord Jeſus:</hi> Now I challenge you to finde one Scripture, which ſaith, The blood of Chriſt cleanſeth ſinners after death; for it is onely effectual to the believers. And now let all who know any thing of faith, judge if it be not you that are ſhuffling and put to the pinch you ſpeak of, who for clearing your deceit, would make people believe that which the Scriptures ſpeak not, but is raiſed in your invention.</p>
            <p>And whereas you charge me with dealing falſly with that Scripture, 1 <hi>John</hi> 1. 7. becauſe I ſay, Doth it ſay any are cleanſed from ſin, while they perſonally act ſin? which I ſay that Scripture doth not, as ſhall appear to all that read it; but quite contrary.</p>
            <p>And whereas you charge me to imitate Satan, who when he came to tempt Chriſt, took what Scripture would ſerve his purpoſe, and leaves out the reſt: I anſwer, Your ſlander is falſe, for I mentioned the ſame Scripture you ſet down, without adding or leaving out, and herein I have not wronged you, neither will the verſe following nor any other Scripture warrant what you ſpeak, <hi>That a man is cleanſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from ſin, while he perſonally acts ſin:</hi> but your words are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the words of Chriſt, who ſaith, <hi>He that committeth ſin, is the ſervant of ſin:</hi> but you ſay, <hi>He may act ſin, and be cleanſed from ſin.</hi> Now who deals deceitfully with the Scripture, and with mens ſouls, and imitates the father of lyes, let the truth judge. And for thoſe words, If we ſay, We have no ſin, we deceive our ſelves, and the truth is not in us; Whoever reads the next words may plainly ſee, that they are ſpoken of a condition before confeſſion and cleanſing;
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:114714:15"/>
elſe the ſame Apoſtle ſhould contradict himſelf, who ſaith, <hi>He that abides in Chriſt ſins not and he that commits ſin is of the Devil,</hi> 1 John 3. 6, 7, 8, 9. <hi>And he that is born of God, ſins not;</hi> which all witneſs againſt your deceit: and for that in <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. and 5. <hi>It is true, no man is juſtified by his own works, for it is he that worketh in us:</hi> but doth that Scripture ſay, He juſtifies the ugodly in his ungodlineſs? or him that by faith became obedient as <hi>Abraham</hi> did? And you that would perſwade people, that Chriſt will juſtifie them in their ungodlineſs, count the blood of Chriſt an unholy thing, which is to cleanſe people from their ſins, and not to juſtifie them in their ſins: and here I charge you by the blood of Chriſt, to be ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to the blood of Chriſt; and here you reaſon to encourage people in ungodlineſs.</p>
            <p>To your tenth <hi>Poſition, No real Saint, but he that is perfect, and perfectly holy in this life, and doth not ſin.</hi> And in your Reply, you are offended with our charging you with pleading for ſin, and you ſay, You foreſaw it. I anſwer, It ſeems ſomething in your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience accuſed you, that we could do no leſs as may appear to all who read your words, who would make people believe, the Saints are real and yet live in ſin: but this is of the ſame with your former, who ſaith. <hi>That while a man is curſing and denying Chriſt, he is in a ſtate of juſtification.</hi> Now what juſtification you own, all may ſee, when you ſay, <hi>He that denies Chriſt, is in a ſtate of juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And whereas you ſay, <hi>To diſcover ſin is not to plead for it:</hi> and many deceitful words you uſe, and brings in a compariſon of a Phyſitian diſcovering a conſumption, to that end that the patient may be healed, and this you ſay is the very caſe between you and <hi>Nayler.</hi> I anſwer, Your compariſon will not hold, for the Phyſitian diſcovers the diſeaſe, that there may be healing. But your diſcovering, is, that none can be free from it while they live; nor do we ſay, You plead for ſin in your diſcovering of ſin; but in that you ſay, <hi>No man ſhall ever be without it:</hi> and here you plead, that men ſhall ſerve the devil as long as they live; for <hi>he that commits ſin is of the devil, and the ſervant of ſin:</hi> and ſuch a one is the ſervant of the devil.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:114714:16"/>And whereas you ſay that <hi>Nayler</hi> will not hear of the Saints being ſick, or under any ſpiritual imperfection; your Charge is falſe: for the Saints growth I own, and the time of a childe I own, and the growth till the overcoming; and do not deny ſeeking after the heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the blood of Chriſt, but witneſs it effectual for cleanſing and overcoming; which you deny, and ſay, that to witneſs perfection and holineſs, and the overcoming of ſin, is really to plead for ſin, and to ſtrengthen the bars of the kingdom of Satan. And that which the Saints have witneſſed, and do witneſs, you would render it under the name of <hi>Conceit,</hi> and charge them to make the blood of Chriſt in vain. But whether do they who witneſs the end for which the blood of Chriſt was given, which is, to <hi>cleanſe from all ſin,</hi> 1 Joh. 1. 7. or they that deny it, make it in vain?</p>
            <p>And whereas you ſay, <hi>The practice of Quakers, both in their ſpeaking and writing, is never to ſend ſouls to the blood of Chriſt, but to their own light to ſave them:</hi> O you filthy ſlanderers, who matter not what you ſpeak againſt the truth! Where did ever the Quakers, either in ſpeaking or writing, deny the blood of Chriſt, or ſend any to their own light to ſave them, but to the light of Chriſt, and to the blood of Chriſt? For what is our own, is darkneſs: but Chriſt the light of the world we witneſs, and this light ſhining out of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <p>And whereas you uſe many words, and bring many Scriptures, as to make people believe that we hold the blood of Chriſt needleſs, or that men can be cleanſed without it; that is your deceit: for all are miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable till they be cleanſed by Chriſt: and then <hi>Who ſhall lay any thing to the charge of Gods elect,</hi> whoſe ſins are taken away by the Lamb of God? And ſuch deny ſelf-righteouſneſ. And though <hi>Paul</hi> did witneſs his warfare, which we witneſs alſo in our meaſure; yet after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward he did witneſs his overcoming, and being more then a conqueror.</p>
            <p>And whereas you talk of covering ſins daily; his ſins who are once covered, are not daily to cover, but once for ever, if he abide in Chriſt, and return not into ſin again; and are made heirs of the righteouſneſs of God: and ſuch deny ſelf-righteouſneſs.</p>
            <p>And whereas you charge us with blaſphemous hereſie, denying the Lord that bought us, railing, pride, lying, reproaching the Ordinance of God, and Meſſengers of Jeſus; we deny it; and this ſhall ſtand for your ſelves. For blaſphemies and hereſies, you that would draw people from the teachings of Chriſt, are guilty of them: and the Lord
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:114714:16"/>
that bought us we own, whom you that are ſold to ſin cannot witneſs. Railing, pride, and lying, we abhor, and witneſs againſt them in you, who live in them, and therefore you hate us. The Ordinance of God we own, but deny your traditions. The Meſſengers of Jeſus we own, and their call, and deny you, who ſcorn the immediate call of Chriſt, and would caſt it off as blaſphemy, on them whom he hath called; and ſo witneſs your ſelves to be of thoſe who run unſent: and here you are diſcovered, and your covering is too narrow, and your bed is too ſhort. And the words of <hi>Job</hi> we own, and deny self-ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification, and witneſs our ſelves juſtified by Chriſt and his righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs brought neer unto us; which is not a broken reed, as you would call it, but will ſtand us in ſtead in the evil day. And our walking with God in his righteouſneſs, is our covering from wrath; for which you reproach us, and caſt it upon us as blaſphemy: but it is, that you may be manifeſt, that you know not the covering of Chriſts righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs and holineſs, in which whoever walk with God, are covered from wrath.</p>
            <p>And whereas you ſay that Chriſt deſtroyed the works of the devil for his people upon the Croſs, and yet men muſt commit ſin while they live; here is your confuſion laid open to all men: and you who live in ſin, which is a work of the devil, he hath not deſtroyed the works of the devil in you: and out of your own mouth be you judged that you are not his people; for the work of the devil is alive in you. And the croſs of Chriſt you know not: for what Chriſt formerly did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy upon the croſs for his people, he doth the ſame now; and ſo is <hi>the ſame yeſterday, to day, and for ever,</hi> Heb. 13. 8. which croſs you that live in your pride, and luſts of the fleſh, will not take up, and therefore the works of the devil remain in you undeſtroyed. And for the Scriptures you alleadge, do any of them ſay that Chriſt hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed the works of the devil for them who live in ſin? for, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ſin, is the work of the devil. And firſt, you ſay Chriſt hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed the works of the devil upon the croſs; and then, you ſay the works of Satan ſhall be deſtroyed in the time appointed of the Father, and he ſhall preſent us ſpotleſs at his coming: which time of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers appointment, and coming of Chriſt to preſent ſpotleſs, you ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to be ignorant of: for the Fathers time is <hi>To day,</hi> to them that will hear his voice. And the <hi>coming of Chriſt without ſin unto ſalvation, and preſenting ſpotleſs,</hi> is witneſſed.</p>
            <p>And whereas you go about to make people believe, that though
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:114714:17"/>
they die the ſervants of ſin, yet they ſhall be compleat in Chriſt, and be made glorious, and perfect, and holy after death, which is your own imagination: here I charge you in the preſence of the living God to be in the Papiſts faith, to encourage people to live in ſin while they live, and for which you have no Scripture; for I challenge you to bring one Scripture, which doth ſay, That perfection and holineſs are reſerved till after death, or that any ſhall inherit them after death; or one Scripture, that ſaies, Men ſhall live in ſin, while they are upon the earth, who cannot witneſs them here; but as men die, ſo ſhall they come to judgement, and ſo ſhall be proceeded againſt, without any ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs added to them after death. And thus you are not afraid to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive ſouls, and hold things contrary to plain Scripture to deceive with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, which at that day you ſhall accompt for, which will be terrible to all deceivers: and whereas you would wreſt thoſe words of Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. 18. <hi>Not one jot or tittle of the Law ſhall paſs away un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til all be fulfilled:</hi> and this you would wreſt, to make the Law void, as though God did not require it to be fulfilled, and you ſay, this was the ſcle and alone work of Chriſt; which work of Chriſt, you know not in your ſelves, who puts it far from you; for they who witneſs the work of Chriſt, they know that he who did fulfil the Law, doth fulfil the it in every generation of the Saints, who believe in him, and ſo by faith the Law is eſtabliſhed, and not made void: and whereas you ſay, It is not ſaid in all the book of God, that the righteouſneſs of the Law is fulfilled in this life, in any Saints: and here I charge you all to be lyers in the preſence of the living God. But you ſay the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry is aſſerted. I anſwer, It ſeems you hold a fulfilling of it after death, but read <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 3, 4. and let the Scripture be witneſs againſt you, which ſaith in plain words, That Chriſt came for that end, to fulfil the Law in the Saints, which they could not do, through the weakneſs of the fleſh; and there is no Scripture that aſſerts the contrary, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out your wreſtings; which I deny, as you have wreſted and turned many Scriptures here to your own deſtruction, and to deſtroy others; turning them into your ſence, to another end then for which the holy Ghoſt gave them forth, for the Spirit of God did never give out the Scripture to plead for ſin while men live, but they are ſo plain to all, your wreſting of them, that I forbear to mention them in particular: and whereas you ſlander us to hold up Popiſh notions, and inherent holineſs, that is your own practiſe, and your own words, which we deny. And you that ſay, May not a man be in part unclean, and yet
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:114714:17"/>
pure and ſpotleſs too, by reaſon of imputation. Here you now ſhew your confuſion; and I command you to ſhew plain Scripture for this without twining. And now let any who ſees your pleading for ſin and uncleanneſs, which Chriſt came to take away, judge if you are not the upholders of what Chriſt came to deſtroy; and here you are Antichriſts, and by your pleading for ſin is the man of ſin diſcovered in you, who pleads for his kingdom, while men live: and how I am a Railer for laying open theſe truths, let any judge where the man of ſin is diſcovered, and you are found faithful to (therein you are in the doctrine of the Papiſts) your Maſter.</p>
            <p>The eleventh <hi>Poſition, That every man in the world hath a light within him ſufficient to guide him to ſalvation, without the help of any outward light or diſcovery.</hi> And in your Reyly you deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully put in that word (<hi>ſaving light</hi>) which is not ſpoken by me, for though Chriſt be the light of the world that enlightens all, yet none are ſaved by him, but who believe and follow him out of the works of darkneſs; but to the reſt it is the condemnation that light is come into world, and they love darkneſs and their evil deeds, and here are you to be condemned with it, who are enemies to the light, and pleads againſt it, and ſo lives in works of darkneſs.</p>
            <p>And whereas you ſay, <hi>None can come except the Father draw them;</hi> it's true, but thoſe drawings, you and all that hate the light, do reſiſt.</p>
            <p>And whereas you ſay, <hi>Every one that hath heard and learned of the Father cometh to me;</hi> It's true, and that's the reaſon why you (who own not the teachings of the Father, but counts it blaſphemy to witneſs his voice) come not to Chriſt, but are at a diſtance from him: and for <hi>John</hi> 1. 4, 5. which you ſay, Is clear againſt me, and you ſay, They were in darkneſs for want of light; but <hi>John</hi> ſaith, <hi>The light ſhined in darkneſs; and he came unto his own, and they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived him not</hi> John 1. And here <hi>John</hi> ſhews, the cauſe why they were in darkneſs, was, becauſe they received not the light, for as many as received him became the ſons of God; and thus what <hi>John</hi> ſaith you hold the contrary: and you ſay that of <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. 19. <hi>This is the condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation that light is come into the world,</hi> is full againſt me; but how that is full againſt my witneſſing every man to have a light, let any man ſee; but you ſure think that people are bound to believe any thing you ſay, without any further trial; but the light is come, and you muſt now lead none, but who are wilfully blinde. And for
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:114714:18"/>
the third branch of my anſwer, <hi>That where the light of Chriſt is there needs no outward diſcovery,</hi> to this you ſay, You have abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly proved, that Chriſt is not in all, nor doth enlighten all. I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, Your proofs are contrary to plain Scripture in this, as in all the reſt; for the Scripture ſaith <hi>Chriſt is in all, Jew and Greek, bond and free,</hi> Col. 3. 11. <hi>And this is the true light that enlightens every one that comes into the world,</hi> John 1. 9. John 8. 12. And you ſay you have fully proved, that all men in the world do need an outward light, and that it is the way of Chriſt to make himſelf known by outward diſcoveries, and you ſay you have proved it by arguments. I anſwer, Your deceitful arguments I deny, and they are no proof to me, nor any that fear God, who receive that truth by the Spirit and not by arguments; but bring one Scripture in plain words: that all men need an outward light, or that an outward diſcovery is the way by which Chriſt makes himſelf known to his people; and till then, I deny you and your Philoſophy: and prove one Saint that ever knew Chriſt ſince his aſcenſion, but by revelation. And what talk you of preaching the Goſpel; who denies the immediate call of Chriſt, or any hearing his voice? or to talke of Officers given for perfecting of the Saints, which ſay, none ſhall ever be perfect while they live? which ſhew you to be none of thoſe Officers given by Chriſt for the perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Saints, for you plead againſt ſuch as witneſs that work and that end.</p>
            <p>And whereas you ſay, That the light ſpoken of 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 19. that <hi>Peter</hi> doth not ſend them to a light within, but to books and words of the Prophets, which Scripture ſhall witneſs againſt your deceit and blindeneſs; for the Apoſtle exhorts them to wait on the light, <hi>til the day dawn, and the day-ſtar ariſe in their hearts;</hi> which is not without nor in books: and if the teſtimony of the old Prophets, was a more ſure word, then that which <hi>Peter</hi> heard from the mouth of God, then it muſt needs follow that the teſtimony of the old Prophets, who ſpoke but darkly of Chriſt, and did not ſee his day, (though they deſired it) muſt be a more ſure teſtimony then the Apoſtles who were his eye-witneſſes, and the words of books a more ſure word, then the voice that came from heaven, which was the immediate voice of God; which blinde abſurdity, all who have the Spirit of propheſie, which is the ſure word and teſtimony of Jeſus ſhall condemn your blindeneſs, who knows not that ſure word of propheſie that was in them.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:114714:18"/>And whereas you wiſh the Reader to obſerve, that <hi>Nayler</hi> cries down the Scriptures as needleſs; here you would have the Reader to obſerve your lyes; for though the letter doth not diſcover Chriſt, but the Spirit; yet it is not uſeleſs, for it is a witneſs againſt your practice, opinions, traditions, and caſts you all amongſt the falſe Prophets and hirelings: and herein it is of uſe and authority, and alſo is a witneſs without againſt all who will not own the witneſs within: nor do I cry down the publiſhing the Goſpel by the Miniſtery, nor the hearing God and his word, but you who deny the immediate call and the word of God coming to any now, denies both the word and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery which we own and witneſs.</p>
            <p>The twelfth <hi>Poſition, That there is no need of any outward teaching, by reading or hearing the Scriptures opened or applyed.</hi> And herein you accuſe me of ſhuffling, railing and lying, becauſe I ſay you apply the promiſes of God to them who are in the firſt birth, and preach them up all believers, and ſay men muſt commit ſin while they are here, and ſow pillows under mens arm-holes: now is not this true of you, who ſprinkle Infants by the faith of their Parents, and calls them your flock, and receives them to your Ordinances? and do you not here preach them up believers, within your liberty or Pariſh, though they live in ſin? and here you ſow pillows under every arm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hole: and then do you not fine them, who refuſe to pay you Tythes or hire? and ſo you prepare war againſt them, who put not into your mouthes. And you hold forth, that none can be free from ſin while they live. Now where are the lyes, or what wrong have I done you? let any that is ſpiritual judge, for lying I abhor, or to wrong any; but I ſpeak the truth of you, as your practice doth witneſs. And in your anſwer to that Scripture, which ſaith, <hi>They ſhall no more teach eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man his neighbour, ſaying, Know the Lord,</hi> Heb. 8. 11. This you ſay doth onely concern the children of God, and ſuch as have their ſins pardoned, wherein you exclude all your Pariſh people from the children of God, and pardon of ſin: for how many have you that are taught of God, and needs not your teaching, (as you ſay?) I deſire your hearers that they would conſider of it, that ſo they might come to the teachings of God, and ſo witneſs the children of God, and ſin pardoned, and ſo to witneſs the everlaſting Covenant, and no need of your teachings.</p>
            <p>And whereas you tell of 4 Arguments and above 30 plain Scriptures, in your <hi>Perfect Phariſee;</hi> Your Arguments I deny, and ſees them
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:114714:19"/>
to be deceit, and there is not one of the thirty, nor in the whole book, that doth plainly witneſs to your way of teaching; but the whole Scriptures are againſt you, and all that teach for hire, and denies the immediate call, and the word of the Lord coming to you<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Jer.</hi> 23. 21, 32. And you ask why the Apoſtle wrote to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> to teach them, if that were the meaning that no man ſhould teach their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour. I anſwer, To draw them to the teaching of Chriſt, as is plain, when he tells them of a growth that need no man to teach them: and though he ſay, You have need that one teach you again, which is the firſt Principle of the Oracles of God, doth he ſay this to continue them in a need of that, (as you would inferre) or to ſhame them, that they were not yet grown up to the teachings of God, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. 1. and out of mans teachings towards perfection?</p>
            <p>And whereas you alledge the exhortation of the Apoſtles, we own it, which was to draw up to the light and teaching, as is plain in their exhorting them to wait for the appearing of Chriſt, who was their light and life, <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 4.</p>
            <p>And whereas you ſay, You preſs all to ſtruggle after that perfection they do not yet enjoy; now how this agrees with your ſaying they ſhall never be perfect while they live, and what encouragement you give them to ſtruggle is evident, who tells them they muſt ſtruggle, but never prevail while they live. And here you are found to be the juglers you ſpeak of, whoſe teaching is yea and nay.</p>
            <p>And whereas you charge me with caſting dirt upon the Scriptures, becauſe I ſay the Holy Ghoſt did not put it into Chapters and Verſes, but the hireling-Prieſts to trade withal: Here you appear to be falſe accuſers, and the railers and lyars you ſpeak on; for I have not ſpoken one word againſt the Scriptures, but own them, as the Holy Ghoſt gave them forth.</p>
            <p>The thirteenth <hi>Poſition, That the Scriptures are not the word of God, but a Declaration of the condition of them that ſpoke them forth.</hi> And in your Reply you alledge many Scriptures, but not one that ſpeaks of a written word, or that the letter is the word; but that it is a Declaration is plain, as <hi>Luk.</hi> 1. 1. 1. <hi>Joh.</hi> 1. 3. and divers other places, where they that had the word in them, declared it in writings to others, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1. 16.</p>
            <p>And whereas you ſay<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The ſeed is the word; it's true, but that ſeed is not the letter, nor can any ſow that ſeed, but where Chriſt is reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in them. And you argue carnally, and ſay, Can the devil take
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:114714:19"/>
Chriſt out of their hearts? I anſwer, Where the devil is received in, there Chriſt departs, and in that ſenſe may be ſaid to be taken away; but if you minde the words that follow, (<hi>Leſt they ſhould believe and be ſaved</hi>) it will appear to be the ſeed of Chriſt, for in what elſe could they be believe to ſalvation, but in Chriſt? and this ſeed is not the letter<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as you would prove it to be: and for that place, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2. 13. where it is ſaid, <hi>That which the Saints heard of the Apoſtles, was not the words of man;</hi> I anſwer, It's true, and that word was Chriſt the word of faith, as is plain, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 6 7 8. neither can you prove that ever the Apoſtles preached any other word, but Chriſt, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>And whereas you ſay, there are two words of God, an eſſential and a declarative word, which is your own language, but the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſpeaks no ſuch words.</p>
            <p>And whereas you accuſe us to deſtroy the Scriptures Divinity and Authority; but is this to deſtroy their Authority, when we ſay, They were ſpoken forth by the Holy Ghoſt, which was in them that ſpoke them forth? and ye would make people believe the letter to be the foundation of the Saints, and hath the Authority over the Soul: and here you deny Chriſt, to eſtabliſh the letter in his ſtead, who is the foundation of Saints, and hath the Authority of Souls; for they who preached Chriſt the foundation, denied themſelves to preach the letter; but your miniſtration is of the letter, who knows no other word, but what you read in books. And this is your foundation you ſtand on, and here it's tried<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and by which you get your living in the world, and here you deny Chriſt, for the letter is not Chriſt.</p>
            <p>And whereas you talk of the commands of God, but his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands you know not, who have them to ſeek in the letter; for his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands is in Spirit, and ever was, and yet this doth not deſtroy the Scriptures<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but witneſs the ſame Spirit that gave them forth, and that which the Saints ſpoke was the word of the Lord, and not the letter, according to their ſeveral meaſures and conditions.</p>
            <p>And whereas you accuſe me to ſay that the words which the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets ſpoke was Chriſt, wherein your deceit appears to all that read my words, for I do not ſay their words were Chriſt, but that Spirit by which they ſpoke was the Spirit of Chriſt. And this is that which I ſpoke of, which came to the Prophets, which you deny to be Chriſt, and therewith the life of Chriſt and the Apoſtles, you are all judged out of truth, and here your deceit<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and blindeneſs, and ſlanders, are laid open for every ſpiritual eye to ſee.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:114714:20"/>The fourteenth <hi>Poſition, That the Spirits are not to be tried by Scriptures.</hi> And here becauſe I ſay that the infallible Spirit, which is the original of all Scriptures, is the trial of all Spirits, from thence you argue, that I ſet the minde and will of the Spirit, in oppoſition to the Spirit, which is falſe; for I ſet the Spirit of God in whom it is in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to all deceitful Spirits; for ſo the Apoſtle bids them who had the Spirit of God, try the deceitful Spirits: and this was not ſpoken to them, who were guided by the Spirit of the world; for ſuch cannot try the Spirits, neither with the letter nor without it, as I have formerly proved: neither did Chriſt ſend them to try his Spirit, when he bad them, <hi>Search the Scriptures:</hi> nor did the <hi>Bereans</hi> try the Spirit of Chriſt, but ſearched the words which <hi>Paul</hi> ſpoke from thoſe Scriptures that declared of Chriſt. And here by the viſible eye they tried viſible words; but the Spirit of God is inviſible, and cannot be tried by any, but thoſe who have it, and are guided by it. And you that would make people be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that all that can read the letter, can try the Spirit of God, would ſet up carnal judges over the Spirit of God; when the Scripture ſaith, <hi>The natural man underſtands not the things of God:</hi> and you confeſs the eternal Spirit to be the trier of Spirits, though formerly you ſeemed to deny it; but ſay your queſtion is, what the Saints had to try the Spirits by. I anſwer, By the ſame Spirit by which they are ſanctified, and prove in Scripture where the Saints are commanded to try the Spirits by any other things, and here ſee your confuſion; for the letter is dead, and ſpeaks nothing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for the Apoſtles ſaid, <hi>They ſerved God in the newneſs of life, and not in the oldneſs of the letter:</hi> and if any man read this letter: and not by the ſame Spirit that gave it forth, he is not able to judge of it, but wreſts it as you do for your ſeveral ends: &amp; if any man read it by the ſame Spirit that gave it forth, it is the Spirit that judgeth of the letter, and not the letter of the Spirit.</p>
            <p>And whereas you talk of trying the doctrines of men by the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; it is true, they that have had the Spirit of God in all ages, have made uſe of the letter, againſt the deceitful doctrines, as we do at this day, and yet this letter is not the judge of the Spirit of God in them, for this were to ſet the letter above the Spirit.</p>
            <p>And whereas you accuſe us to exclude the Scriptures, becauſe we ſay the holy Ghoſt is the original of them, which ſlander is falſe; for hereby we confeſs and own the Scripture to be given forth by the holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:114714:20"/>And whereas you ſay the light which a ſpiritual man hath<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> is a Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture-light; I anſwer, A ſpiritual mans light, is the light of Chriſt, and is infallible, and cannot be altered; and therefore all that are guided by it are one, where there is no diſputes nor janglings; but you that have your light from what you gather out of the letter, are confuſed amongſt your ſelves<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> adding to it your own meanings, for your own ends, and do not ſpeak one and the ſame things, but every man accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his imaginations of the letter, ſo he judgeth, and ſo he wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippeth, and here are you Teachers of the world divided in your ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral judgements, and your ſeveral worſhips. And thus you are putting meaning upon <hi>Paul</hi>'s words, where he ſaith, <hi>He is preſent in Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> which you go about to deny by your meanings, and ſo would make <hi>Paul</hi> a lyar like your ſelves; but they who believes your wreſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings before <hi>Paul</hi>'s words, are blinde like you: and ſo with the Apoſtles light you are all judged, and ſo the blinde leads the blinde. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I ſay the Spirit of God was the trier of Spirits before the letter was, therefore you would make people believe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that I hold forth that the Word is not to be regarded, nor the Law looked upon, nor the Scripture heeded; and when you have thus falſly ſlandered, you ſay you leave the Reader to laugh at it: it ſhews that light Spirit rules in you; but whilſt you are thus in your laughter, and perſwading o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to laugh alſo, all that fear God may mourn to ſee your doctrine<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to ſee you profeſs the name of the Lord who is holy, and you to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther up ſuch filthy conſequences as theſe, to ſlander the truth withal<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and when you have done, make it a matter of laughter; but the day is at hand<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> when your laughter ſhall be turned into howling and weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and then wo unto you, and thoſe that laugh with you. And for what I ſaid of your ſeveral judgements, and worſhips, and imagined Gods according to your ſeveral judgements, it is true, as all that take notice of you and your diviſions through the whole Nation may witneſs with me, for the true God is but one, and his worſhip one.</p>
            <p>And whereas you ſay you hold the head, the Lord Jeſus, it is falſe, for they who hold him for their head, the Lord and Maſter, denied to be called Maſters themſelves amongſt the Saints, or of the world, but owned one Maſter, which is the Head, which is Chriſt, and they were all brethren, neither did they exerciſe authority one over a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, as the Heathen do, neither were they bowed to and worſhipt with cap and knee, as you are, and do to others, for they had one Maſter, whom they worſhipped and bowed their knee to, which was
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:114714:21"/>
ſpiritual, in whom they believed, which faith they had not in reſpect of perſons, but you are enemies to that faith, neither can you believe, <hi>who receive honor one of another,</hi> John 5. 44. and here you hold not the Head the Lord, but walk as Lords your ſelves amongſt your hearers, which <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> never did, whoſe conditions you talk ſo much on: and this is not my venom but a true witneſs againſt your unrighteous practice.</p>
            <p>And whereas you talk of things hard to be underſtood in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, which the unſtable and unlearned wreſt: It is true, and you are thoſe unlearned, who were never taught of God, nor heard his voice, but reproach them that have; and you are they who wreſt theſe Scriptures to your own deſtruction, and not rightly underſtanding them, cannot diſcover every Spirit; nay, you are ſo blinde, that you cannot diſcover that ſpirit in you that acts you in covetouſneſs, pride, ſlander, envie and perſecution, is the ſpirit of the devil; and that ſpirit that acts you to plead for ſin while men live, to be the ſpirit of the man of ſin; and though you talk of the <hi>word</hi> that is <hi>ſweeter then the hony and the hony combe,</hi> and ſo have ſtoln <hi>Davids</hi> words, yet that word you know not, nor that ſweetneſs of it, who deny the word of the Lord coming to you, and know no word but the letter: for that word which <hi>David</hi> ſpeaks of, was within him, and not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out him, which word I witneſs, and its ſweetneſs.</p>
            <p>And whereas you charge me to ſet a gloſs upon that Scripture, <hi>Iſa. 8. 20. To the Law and to the teſtimony, if they ſpeak not according to this word it is becauſe there is no light in them:</hi> and becauſe I ſay, <hi>The Law of God in the new Covenant is written in the hearts of men,</hi> which is plain in the Scriptures, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8. 10. Therefore you ſay, I overturn all Scripture, ſo that for me to ſpeak Scripture and witneſs the promiſe of God in the new Covenant, and the end of the old, by your deceit you would make it to overturn Scripture; and you ſay it hath reference to the Law written in tables of ſtone; 'ts true, and that was in the old Covenant a type of the new, and of that Law that ſhould be written in mens hearts in the new Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, &amp; you that would deny the new Covenant to eſtabliſh the old, make it appear that you are blinde and ignorant of that Covenant, and that pure Law which is within written by the Lord in the heart, and are in your own righteouſneſs and Covenant of works, and ſo have no light in you, whoſe light and Law is without, and all that are ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al againſt you, who ſaies herein I overturn all Scriptures, who wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:114714:21"/>
the Scriptures fulfilled, and as for <hi>John Gilpin</hi> whom you ſay is delivered out of the ſnares of the devil, and would make him a ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling-block to the truth, his practice ſince hath ſhewed how he hath been delivered out of the ſnares of the devil, and the judgement of God hath overtaken him: and whether they conſulted with <hi>John Gilpin</hi> againſt Chriſt, who cauſed his book to be printed over again, and framed it at the firſt, the truth may eaſily judge, and their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſhall be according to their works.</p>
            <p>To your fifteenth <hi>Poſition, That there ought to be no ſence, meaning, or expoſition given, or ſtudying of the Scripture.</hi> And in your Reply you ſay, The Scriptures are in ſome places given out darkly, and when you have done, you ſay, it is from the darkneſs that lies on the Spirits of the Saints. Here is your confuſion and dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: and for the key of <hi>David</hi> you ſpeak on, it is not committed into the hands of any hirelings as you are, nor ever was, but where Chriſt is, and ſuch live the life of the Scriptures, and ſo open them in their converſation, as well as words: and till your lives witneſs what you preach, you ſhut them to others, and not open them. And how long your generation have been about opening them, all may ſee, and yet they are ſhut from your ſelves, and you cannot agree about them, and then how will you open them to others? but who waits for that Spirit that gave them forth, ſhall not need you and your openings, but by that Spirit will deny you and your openings, and with that Spirit judge you all, and the blindeneſs of you hearers: your own practice ſhews what openers you are; for they are a book ſealed to your wiſdom and carnal learning. Therefore let them alone as they are for they are of no private interpretation, nor are they committed to you to open, nor doth any Scripture you alledge prove any ſuch thing.</p>
            <p>And whereas you ſay you have the infallible Spirit dwelling in you; I anſwer, Where that Spirit is, it is one, and admits of no diſputes and janglings; but ſpeaks one and the ſame thing in all that have it in their meaſure; but your diviſions amongſt your ſelves witneſs what Spirit acts in you, and your pride, covetouſneſs, and conformities to the world; for that Spirit which is infallible, leads out of the world, and faſhions of it, and conforms to Chriſt; and they who judge by that Spirit, deny the wiſdom and learning of the world or to enrich themſelves by it.</p>
            <p>The ſixteenth <hi>Poſition: They cry down baptiſm with water and the Lords Supper, as being but types and ſhadows, ceaſing upon the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:114714:22"/>
appearance of Chriſt in them.</hi> And in your Reply you quarrel that I ſhould ſay, <hi>Paul</hi> knew what he ſaid, when he ſaid, <hi>Chriſt ſent me not to baptize, but to preach, 1 Cor.</hi> 1. 17. and you ſay, This is to heap ſin upon <hi>Peter</hi> and the reſt of the Apoſtles: but that <hi>Paul</hi> by ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the truth, or I by ſpeaking it after him, doth thereby heap ſin upon <hi>Peter,</hi> is a ſtrange inference, but it is like the reſt; for there is no truth that I ſpeak, but you can inferre a ſlander from it, and how many times in your book have you ſlandered me for ſpeaking plain Scripture? but it is to manifeſt you to be what you are.</p>
            <p>And whereas you ſay we cry down baptiſme and the Lords Supper: It is falſe, for the baptiſm of <hi>John</hi> we own, which is with water, and the baptiſm of Chriſt, with the holy Ghoſt and fire, we own, and the Supper of the Lord we own, and our ſaith feeds upon him, and the eating of his fleſh, and drinking of his blood is our life, <hi>John</hi> 6. 53, 54. and we deny your faith, which you ſay is nouriſhed by bread and wine which is carnal; and your ſprinkling of Infants we deny, which you ſay, You can clear up to be an Ordinance of Chriſt, but doth not, nor can do it.</p>
            <p>The ſeventeenth <hi>Poſition, That there is no mediate call of the Miniſtery.</hi> And you ſay, I contradict my ſelf, becauſe I ſay, That the ordaining of Elders, by the direction of the Spirit of God, was not by man; which I again affirm, That it was not by man, nor of man, nor any created power; but by the Spirit of God in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, which did impower them with the gift of the holy Ghoſt to them who were ordained, and this was not of man, but of God.</p>
            <p>And whereas you would prove your mediate call from this, it will not ſerve your turn, who are either called by the curſed Biſhops, or by earthly Magiſtrates, or elſe you call one another by your own wills, but no appointment of God nor gift of the holy Ghoſt, is wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed amongſt you.</p>
            <p>And whereas you deny that the late commiſſion did ever pretend to put any in the Office of a Miniſter, here all the North may witneſs againſt you, that you care not what you ſay to excuſe your ſelves and accuſe others, though never ſo falſe. Did not you and thoſe that were in commiſſion call them before you, and examined and appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed whom you would, and denied whom you would at will and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure? and your partiality in it, the North can witneſs; and now you deny it: be aſhamed and confounded before all men, you ſhameleſs creatures: this you may call railing, as you do the reſt, where you are
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:114714:22"/>
told of your deceit. And for your fifty five proofs you tell of, which you ſay are not all anſwered: I anſwer, Thoſe that might ſeem to make for your purpoſe are anſwered, and for many other you bring, they are ſo full againſt the end for which you alledge them, that they may anſwer themſelves, before all that know any thing of Scriptures, and to their judgement I leave them, and ſhall not trouble my ſelf or others, with things to ſo little purpoſe. And for your ſending and proving your falſe accuſations, under hand and ſeal, as you call it, here you ſhew what Spirit acts in you, who purſue ſuch unjuſt things with ſuch eagerneſs, which none of the Saints of God ever did, but your reward ſhall be as your work is, and time ſhall clear the truth, when you have vented your envie.</p>
            <p>Now to that you call our Principles.</p>
            <p>And firſt, <hi>Not to ſalute any.</hi> And here you accuſe us to deny high-way ſalutes, and when you have done, you ſay, High-way ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutes is our known practiſe; but how doth this agree? honeſty would never have accuſed us to deny what is our known practice, unleſs you could have proved, that we had denied to ſalute any, as you falſly accuſe us; for the ſalutation of the Saints we own and practice, and deny your heatheniſh cuſtomes, that are uſed without the fear of God.</p>
            <p>And whereas you bring the practice of ſome in the old Teſtament, to overturn the Commands of Chriſt in the new: I anſwer, No con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary practice of any, (though the beſt of Saints) can be a ground for me to break the Command of Chriſt; neither had they whom you inſtance, as <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Abigal,</hi> any command for what they did to bow down, or fall to the ground; but rather did it out of fear and weakneſs. Now if any had alledged theſe to thoſe whom Chriſt ſent out, had that been a ground for them to have broken Chriſts Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, to follow their practice without command? and it is the ſame now. Chriſt who hath ſent us forth, hath commanded us to deny your vain cuſtoms, and not to ſalute any by the way: and this we witneſs and practice, whatever they did in the old time: and here we leave you who are in the world to your traditions of the world, &amp; follow Chriſt, &amp; ſo witneſs againſt all the vanities out of which we are called. And for that place in 2 <hi>Joh.</hi> 10. which you would alledge to keep up the worlds cuſtomes, which is clear againſt you<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for the Apoſtle there commands, <hi>Not to bid God ſpeed to any tranſgreſſor that doth not abide in the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:114714:23"/>
doctrine of Chriſt, and who hath not the Father and the Son;</hi> for if they bade God ſpeed to any of them, they were partakers of their evil deeds. Now they who fear God, had need take heed whom they bid God ſpeed to for few are found who have in them the Father and the Son, and are no tranſgreſſors: and now how this makes for your God ſpeed to all, any that fear God may ſee, and be warned of your deceit, leſt they partake of other mens evil deeds. And ſo it's plain the Saints were forbidden to ſalute any but Saints, though you call it <hi>Publican</hi>-like.</p>
            <p>And whereas you ſay in <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. 37. is a command <hi>to ſalute all;</hi> I anſwer, If that was ſo as you ſpeak, A general command to ſalute all, then doth Chriſt contradict himſelf, when he commands, <hi>Not to ſalute any by the way:</hi> and ſo you will make Chriſt yea &amp; nay; but it is plain that Chriſt is there exhorting to love, and not to ſalutation, wherein he would have them to exceed the Heathen, who ſhewed their partiality in ſaluting their friends onely, which was a token of their love to be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial; but if this were a Command of Chriſt, To ſalute all, and bind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to them who had received a command to the contrary (which we witneſs) then thoſe who obeyed his Command, <hi>Not to ſalute any,</hi> Luke 10. 4. was guilty of the breach of it, which to affirm, was to make Chriſt ſay and unſay: and beſides, there is not a word in it of ſaluting by the way, which is the thing you are to prove, which we ſay, We are forbidden.</p>
            <p>And whereas you ſay, You ſalute the poor as well as the rich; here let your practice witneſs againſt you, who bow to the rich with cap and knee, and worſhip them, and call them Maſters, but do you ſo to the poor? and here you are the heathen. And becauſe I ſay, What we do, we do it not from the commands that were given to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but by his command to us, by whom we are ſent forth; and this you ſay is a myſtery of iniquity, and utterly to ſhake off the authority of the word, and you boaſt much of a great advantage you have got by theſe words: but you ſee not your own blindeneſs, which is apparent, for you ſay, This was a particular command; now inſtance in Scripture, where any Saint did take up any particular command by imitation, but every particular Saint had his particular command from God, which he was to obey; and if all the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular commands that was given to the Saints in Scripture be binding to us in this generation, then why do not you obſerve them? as <hi>Iſaiah</hi> went three yeers naked, why do not you do ſo? and why are not you without money, braſs, two coats and ſhooes, and many ſuch-like com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands?
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:114714:23"/>
And now what doth all your Scriptures prove? It is true, what is written, is for our learning, that as they waited upon God, for their commands what to do, and did obey, ſo we ſhould do likewiſe, &amp; the diſobedient ſhould warn us not to diſobey, <hi>Mat. 15. 9, Iſa.</hi> 29. 13. And thus you have laid open your ſelves to be ignorant of the word of God and his commands to you, and all your obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence is imitation and tradition<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſo in vain you worſhip. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I ſay, If we were commanded to forbear wearing ſhoes, we ſhould be made willing to obey in that, as well as in other things which we are commanded: and you ſay, This is to caſt off the yoke of Chriſt and break his bonds aſunder: now if our willingneſs to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey his commands be to caſt off his yoke, let the wiſe judge, and here your charge ſhall appear to all to be falſe; for to obey the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of Chriſt, is not to deny the authority of the Scripture, (as you would ſlander us) but it eſtabliſhes the Scriptures authority, for herein we witneſs the ſame obedience, and the ſame commanding power with all Saints; and you reckon up many that have been made ſignes and wonders to this generation, as ſome have gone naked, and the like<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8. 18. which you would caſt upon the truth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to make it odious to people: and you bring many Scriptures, and wreſt them to your own ends: to which I anſwer, The command of God to them that know him, is of more force to binde them to obey, then your ſubtil arguings and wreſtings to diſobey, and had you lived in the times of the Prophets, you would have reproached them, for obeying and being made ſignes in the ſame things, as <hi>Iſa.</hi> 20. and others in other things, which your generation then counted madneſs, as you do now; and perſecuted them for it, as you do now; but it is no wonder why you ſhould thus reproach us for obeying God, when you are not afraid to contradict God himſelf in what he ſaith, and give him the lye; for when he ſaith, <hi>My ſervant Iſaiah hath walked naked and bare-foot,</hi> Iſa. 20. you go about to prove that he was not naked; and when God ſaith, <hi>The Egyptians and the Ethiopians ſhall be carried captive naked and barefoot, even with their but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tocks uncovered to their ſhame,</hi> and you deny, and ſay, they took but off their beſt apparel, and left them ſuch as was neceſſary to cover their ſhame; and thus what God ſaith, you ſay the contrary, and go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to make him a lyar, and perſwades people to believe your ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til imaginations before Gods plain words: and here you ſhew the ſerpent, who contraries God in all things, and ever did, and not onely
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:114714:24"/>
here, but in all your books, your reaſoning and proving are for ſin<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and againſt plain Scripture, and any that reads them may ſee that I ſpeak the truth of you, though you may call it railing. And you bring 1 <hi>Tim. 2. 9. That women adorn themſelves in modeſt apparel and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briety.</hi> And this you bring to caſt upon them that obey the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of God, but you might uſe it nearer home amongſt your own wives, who go in their hoods, vails and rings, which is forbiden, and is not modeſty, but pride; but theſe whom you reproach, go in modeſt apparel, though ſome be made as ſignes to you who live in pride: and this is done by a call from God, contrary to their own wills, though you who deny the word coming to you be ignorant of it, as all the falſe Prophets ever were. And for that you caſt upon <hi>Thomas Holms,</hi> that he ſhould ſay, That it was not he that went naked, but God; It is of the ſame root with the reſt, and will not be believed by any but your own generation.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Principle, <hi>Not giving any outward token of reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to Magiſtrates, Parents, Maſters, or any other.</hi> To which I anſwer, Reverence and obedience to Magiſtrates, Parents, Maſters, and others<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> we own according to the Scriptures, but to bow down and worſhip the creature, which God hath forbidden, that we deny; and though you who love greetings and bowing to you, would make people believe it's no ſin, yet they that fear God and worſhip him alone, know it to be a ſin; and <hi>Mordecai</hi> had rather die, and all the ſeed of the <hi>Jews</hi> be cut off, then do it, though the King commanded it; and though you ſay, It's a ridiculous application of that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, <hi>Thou ſhalt not bow down and worſhip,</hi> yet the Apoſtle owns it. And ſaith, <hi>If you reſpect perſons, you commit ſin, and are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced of the Law as tranſgreſſors:</hi> now what Law do ſuch tranſgreſs, if it be not this which convinceth, <hi>That no worſhip is to be given to any but God,</hi> not to mens perſons? but theſe wreſtings are as the reſt, to encourage to do what God forbids; for Chriſt ſaith, <hi>How can you believe, that receive honor one of another?</hi> neither did he nor any of his ever reſpect mens perſons, nor any that is in the faith of Chriſt, <hi>James</hi> 2. 1. but plainly forbids it, both Chriſt and the Apoſtles; which you plead for, and appear to be of a contrary ſpirit, for the Spirit of God where it is, pleads for the worſhip of God alone, for he is no reſpecter of perſons, nor any that is guided by his Spirit; but they that are guided by the ſpirit of the world, pleads for the worlds worſhips and cuſtoms; and where the ſerpent is, he would
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:114714:24"/>
be worſhipped; but the Spirit of Chriſt where it is, keeps the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture upright to God, and not to bow to pride. And notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your light and ſcornful words againſt <hi>A. P.</hi> for ſaying, there is a power without perſons, yet the Saints know that there is a power which is of God, to which they are ſubject for conſcience ſake whether there be any perſons to execute that power or no: for many times the perſons who ſhould have ſet up that power which is of God, have ſet up their wills inſtead of it, and ſo have turned the edge of the ſword, (put into their hands) againſt them that do well, which is appointed by God for a terrour to evil doers, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 3. and when ſuch perſons have ruled, God hath ſent his ſervants to witneſs againſt the perſon and his practice, but the power they are ſtill ſubject to, for conſcience ſake, which is one, and is not changed nor corrupted, though the perſon be; for it remains, and is one with that in the conſcience, and that in the conſcience owns and honours it where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it is, and ſo in ſetting up that power which is of God, is the perſon honoured, (in the ſight of all that fear God) and not in ſetting up himſelf: but you who look upon the perſon as your rule, and not the power, change as mens mindes change, and ſuch will be of the ſame minde with the powers of the earth, turn what way they will, and by theſe the Saints who are faithful to God and his power, have alwaies ſuffered, but theſe will never ſuffer for any truth.</p>
            <p>The third Principle, <hi>That no man muſt have the title of Maſter,</hi> which is falſe, for Maſters and ſervants we own, but to call any Maſter out of a flattering title, or for his riches, or his pride or great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, this we deny, being expreſsly forbidden of Chriſt, both in us, and in the Scriptures.</p>
            <p>And whereas you ſay, You have brought at leaſt ten Scriptures out of the new Teſtament to prove calling men Maſters; I ſay You cannot inſtance one Scripture without wreſting, that ever commands it after Chriſt forbad it; but here, as in the reſt of your book<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> you would turn the Scriptures againſt the plain commands of Chriſt to maintain your pride, and here you are diſcovered to be the Miniſters of Antichriſt, and pleads for his kingdom, and worſhips, againſt Chriſt and his commands. And for the four things you ſay we charge upon you, (<hi>viz.</hi>) 1. That ye love the higheſt places in the Synagogues. 2. That ye wear long robes. 3. Stand praying in the Synagogues. 4. That you preach for hire.</p>
            <p>And whereas you ſay You have proved theſe to be the proper guilt
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:114714:25"/>
of the Phariſees; I anſwer, There are many more may be added to them, which were marks of falſe teachers, which you practice, and then what difference of the Phariſees and you? for one ſpirit acts to one and the ſame things in you both, and one Spirit of Chriſt witneſſeth againſt you both, to be in one condemnation. And for other things you ſay we charge you with, as going to Univerſities, uſing an hour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glaſs, preaching upon a text<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> not uſing the language of the Scriptures in thouing a particular, running to the powers of the world to protect you: Now are not theſe things true of you,? and then what need I ſay any more to them? And as for ſtealing the word from your neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, what word have you elſe but what you ſteal, who denies the word of the Lord coming to you, and the immediate call, and ſcorns it in them who witneſs it? which none ever did but the falſe Prophets, who ſtole the word from the true Prophets: and here your own mouths ſhall witneſs to what I ſay, in the ſight of all men: and for the pure language you ſpeak of is not thou and thee; I anſwer, The Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture-language is the pure language, given out by the pure Spirit, though <hi>Babylon</hi> hath another language of it's own, and denies the Scriptures, but that language is confuſion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and here are you, who <hi>Ye</hi> one, and <hi>Thou</hi> another but the Scripture-language you own not.</p>
            <p>And now to that you call our Practices.</p>
            <p>The firſt Practice, <hi>Quaking,</hi> and here you adde, <hi>groveling on the ground, and foming at the mouth</hi> to be our practice: and to prove this, you bring <hi>John Gilpin,</hi> and <hi>William More,</hi> Prieſt of <hi>Kellit.</hi> I anſwer, Your witneſſes are ſuitable to your ſlander; but all that ever have been at our meetings, yea, thoſe of your own, that have come to ſpie, ſhall witneſs againſt <hi>Gilpin,</hi> and <hi>William More,</hi> and you, that thoſe are not our practice, and the whole country ſhall more and more ſee into your lying ſlanders.</p>
            <p>And whereas you ſay, <hi>Quaking is our great perfection;</hi> It's falſe, for Chriſt is our perfection, though quaking and trembling we own to be a condition the Saints paſſed through, as is plain in Scripture<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> elſe ſhould we deny the Scripture as you do, though you uſe it as a name of reproach.</p>
            <p>The ſlanders of <hi>William</hi> may eaſily be diſproved by what follows.</p>
            <p>I <hi>Jane Withers</hi> was moved of the Lord to go to the Steeple-houſe of <hi>Kellit,</hi> to ſpeak to Prieſt <hi>Moor</hi> theſe words, <hi>Thou art the beaſt
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:114714:25"/>
that all the world worſhips and wonders after: the plagues of God muſt be poured upon thee.</hi> When theſe words came to me, the power of the Lord ſeized upon me; but the deceit prevailed ſo over me, that I did not obey at the firſt movings; but the power of the Lord ſo ſeized on me again, that I was bound about my body above the middle, as if I had been bound with chains, and it was ſaid to me, <hi>That if I went not I ſhould repent it, and he ſhould know it;</hi> and in the afternoon I was forced to go, and as I went in at the door, I ſhould have ſaid, <hi>The plagues of God muſt be poured upon thee,</hi> but I did not ſpeak the words then; and then the power of the Lord came upon me: but in that Prieſt <hi>Moor</hi> ſaies, I was in a trance, it is a lye, for I was as ſenſible all the while as ever I was; and for foming at the mouth I did not, that is a lye; but for the working of the power of the Lord in my body I deny not; and two of the Prieſts own hearers which were cloſe by me, we ſent for, hearing this lying ſlander was ſent to be printed, being examined whether or no they ſaw her ſome at the mouth, the one of them did affirm that it was a lye, and ſhe laid me on her lap; and the other ſaid, She ſaw no ſuch thing; but the Prieſt went his way, and I went after him &amp; then I ſpoke the words that was commanded, and as ſoon as I had ſpoken them, the power ceaſed; and the maid that <hi>Moor</hi> ſent to <hi>George Fox,</hi> which carried the lyes to him, one<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of the women, <hi>Annes Clapin,</hi> one of his hearers, ſaid ſhe was a lyar, and it did not matter what ſhe ſaid<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; this is <hi>Moor</hi>'s ground to write his letter upon to the Prieſt of <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> and they put it in print to miniſter forth his lyes, that their folly might be made manifeſt to all the Country, and truth confirmed, and the deceit trodden upon. And <hi>Moor</hi> which ſent his lying wench, as his own hearers calls her, ſhe came to me three times to <hi>Robert Wither's,</hi> and ſhe ſcoft<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſhe was asked if Chriſt taught her to ſcoff, and ſhe ſaid, He did teach her to ſcoff; and before her face it was written down, and ſhe was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied to talk of the Scriptures that is a ſcoffer. And the lyer would have known, what Scripture there had been, for foming at the mouth, and wherever did he read of any ſuch, unleſs it were ſuch that were poſſeſſed with the devil, ſhe ſaid he denied that any of theirs did, till <hi>Jane Withers</hi> was pointed out, and then ſhe ſaid he confeſſed it.</p>
            <p>Oh thou lyer and ſlanderer, God will make thee an example to all lyers, and they that witneſs for <hi>Jane Withers,</hi> which are of the Prieſts own hearers; ſome will witneſs againſt thee to be a lyer<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and one that matters not what thou ſpeakeſt; and before <hi>James</hi>'s face, ſhe
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:114714:26"/>
was proved a ſlanderer and a lyer, and lying is a ſin, and he denies it; and to ſay he confeſſed that <hi>Jane Withers</hi> fomed at the mouth, is a lye, and many will witneſs againſt it. And here thou <hi>Moor</hi> that art for the lake, who fathers lyes, thy own hearers will witneſs againſt thee.</p>
            <p>And whereas you ſay ſhe asked him if lying was a ſin, here in this you are proved to be lying and ſinning, and ſo with the juſt you lyers are judged, and condemned for the lake eternally, though thou may think a while to pleaſe the world. But Oh thou Harlot, thy wo and miſery is coming.</p>
            <p>Some Scriptures given forth about <hi>travailing, as, I ſaid, I will cry as a travailing woman,</hi> Iſa. 42. 14. Iſa. 63. 1. <hi>travailing in the greatneſ; of his ſtrength.</hi> Rom. 8. 22. <hi>travaileth in pain toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> Micah 4. 3. <hi>She which travaileth hath brought forth.</hi> Iſa. 21. 3. <hi>as the pargs on a woman in travail;</hi> Habakkuk, <hi>whoſe belly trembled.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And here <hi>Moor</hi> and his meſſenger ſeems to be ignorant of the Letter, and wonderers which are to periſh. And the Prieſts of <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſtle,</hi> which ſaid they could not but ſmile at <hi>James Nayler,</hi> hath declared themſelves to be the mockers that ſhould come in the laſt time: and the maid which they printed her lyes, ſaid that Chriſt taught her to ſcoff, before many witneſſes. And here they ſhew what gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration they are on; like Prieſt, like people; for they who dwell in the Truth can ſcarcely paſs up and down, for your ſcoffing generation; but to us your reproaches are great riches, and knowing that you and your generation is for condemnation, which ſtumble at the light.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Practice, <hi>Railing,</hi> and you inſtance theſe words, <hi>Thou art damned, and I ſee the devil in thy face;</hi> and this you ſay is the firſt ſalute to all we meet with: to which I anſwer, Thouſands in the Country ſhall witneſs you falſe accuſers, which we have met with, paſt by and ſpoke not one word to them: but you are ſhameleſs, and care not what you ſay againſt us; and for words which have been ſpoken to ſome of you, which you call railing, you will finde them one day to be no railings, but the language of the Spirit upon the head of the man of ſin in you, though for the preſent you will not own them.</p>
            <p>The third Practice, <hi>Their pretending upon all occaſions, to be ſent by a ſpecial commiſſion from God.</hi> To this I anſwer, What have
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:114714:26"/>
you to do to ſpeak of, or how can you judge of them that are ſent by God, who deny the immediate call, and ſcorns it, and knows it not? can you judge of that you know not, who knows not the word of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> nor his call?</p>
            <p>And whereas you ſay, <hi>I knew not the things in particular, and yet I take the boldneſs to call them lyes;</hi> I anſwer, Your words are falſe; for I ſay, I knew not the things in particular, and therefore could ſay little; but finding your book ſtufe with lyes and untruths, gave me cauſe to ſee many of theſe to be like the reſt, which is not to call them lyes as you ſay, and now judge of your own conſcience as you ſay. And for denying that any that were before the Magiſtrates were invited to any of your houſes, are not my words; but the words of one who was before the Magiſtrates, as will appear in the margent, though you ſo raſhly caſt it upon me; and here it may be ſeen who it is that ruſheth upon a lye, which you charge me to do, but are found the lyers your ſelves: neither did you invite any of them which were called before the magiſtrates, as appears both by their own witneſs, and your own confeſſion, for you ſay it was <hi>Tho. Tayler</hi> you invited, who was not then called before the Magiſtrates, nor impriſoned. And you that call it immodeſt for the Saints to greet one another with a kiſs, and would ſlander by it, may as well accuſe the Apoſtle for immodeſt, who exhorteth the Saints to it, and was this the thing you kept ſo cloſe, when you ſaid, (<hi>to ſay no more?</hi>) It ſeemed by thoſe words to have been ſome hainous thing, and not the Apoſtles exhortation, and Saints practice, but you want matter to accuſe of. And for what <hi>Wallis</hi> ſaid, there was witneſs enough; and all your fending and prov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cannot ſtop the truth, but make your deceit more appear. And for your reaſon you ſhew, why you called your book<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>The Perfect Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſee;</hi> and you ſay, <hi>That title is moſt properly applied to us;</hi> I anſwer, It's moſt properly applied to them who are found to walk in the ſteps of the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> and whether that be us or you, let your practices judge, and all that ſee us, and all your practice ſhall witneſs with me, that I have not wronged or belyed you, as you would make people believe, but let any honeſt heart, who reads both our books judge betwixt us who are the ſlanderers, lyers and railers, which you would caſt upon me<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but the thing is evident to all, and you cannot be hid, who have nothing to judge withal, and it is of God to diſcover you to all, that you may deceive no longer. Bleſſed be our God who is revealing the man of ſin, who hath acted in a myſtery, and is deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:114714:27"/>
his people from your mouthes, and redeeming them to himſelf, who is holy: praiſes be to our God for ever, and let all the children of light praiſe him for ever.</p>
            <p>And if any ſcruple why the ſervants of God ſhould be made ſigns and wonders to this generation, I refer them, for ſatisfaction, to a printed paper, called <hi>A Wo to Kendal in the County of Weſtmore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> in which you ſhall finde the dear ſervants of God made ſignes and wonders, to the generation of the wicked then, and confounding the ſepents wiſdom, acting ſtrange things by the immediate commands of God, into which the wiſdom of the world could never enter.</p>
            <p>God hath made many as ſignes among you, as to go naked in your Steeple-houſes, in your markets, in your ſtreets, as many in the Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern parts, which is a figure to you of all your nakedneſs.</p>
            <p>Prieſts, in your firſt page, you ſay, <hi>It is their greateſt work to deny his righteouſneſs fulfilled in his perſon, to be imputed to you for your juſtification.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rep.</hi> What righteouſneſs is there imputed to the workers of iniquity, which are curſed? the righteouſneſs of Chriſt we own, which he fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in his own perſon, who is the Lord our righteouſneſs, &amp; we through him are become the righteouſneſs of God, and from this you Prieſts are ſhut out, who would do as your fathers did, who perſecuted the Lord of glory; and I charge you here in the preſence of the living God to be lyers; for what Chriſt fulfilled and came to fulfil, we own, which Chriſt is the ſame yeſterday, to day, and for ever: and the ſame Miniſtery, and the ſame immediate call we witneſs, and have all the Prophets<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Apoſtles, and Chriſt the Corner-ſtone to witneſs us in the ſame; and all you reprobates, and all your weapons you ſtrike with againſt the truth, do but confirm us, and eſtabliſh the innocent, and confirm the truth againſt all you oppoſers.</p>
            <p>Prieſts, you are ſpeaking of <hi>faith being ſwallowed up in viſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I charge you to ſhew ſuch an expreſſion in Scripture amongſt all the Saints which was in faith.</p>
            <p>Prieſts, whereas you ſay, <hi>That George Fox called Mr. Nichols hypocrite in Carlile, though he never ſaw his face.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here I charge you all Prieſts to be confuſed. And you ſay, <hi>How doth this bottom upon Chriſt, who gave it to none, but ſuch as they had a particular knowledge of?</hi> Here I charge you to be contrary to Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt, contrary to the Apoſtles, for Chriſt ſaid, <hi>Judge not
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:114714:27"/>
according to outward appearance as the Phariſees did.</hi> And here I prove you to be <hi>Phariſees:</hi> and the Apoſtle ſaid, <hi>He was preſent in Spirit beholding the order of the Saints,</hi> though he never ſaw their faces: and here I judge with the Spirits of the Apoſtles, to be out of their life. And you ſay, <hi>That Chriſt gave that title as hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite to Herod and the teachers of falſe doctrine.</hi> Now to you I ſpeak: The Scripture it ſelf, and Chriſts words in it, ſhall be your judge to be in the ſteps of the <hi>Phariſees</hi> and falſe teachers, and in the nature of <hi>Herod<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> which are called of men Maſters, as the hypocrites were<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and hath the cheif places in the aſſemblies<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſtand praying in the Synagogues, which are painted with the Prophets, Chriſts and the Apoſtles words, as your fathers were with the Prophets words, laying heavy burthens upon the people, as ſome of your fellow-Prieſts have impriſoned ſome, becauſe they would not pay Tythes, which are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended teachers: and here you are under the wo which Chriſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced againſt your fathers, as you may read <hi>Mat.</hi> 23. and ſo with all the children of the light you are judged, and with the light of Chriſt you are condemned to be out of his doctrine eternally, and for condemnation of old with the light, which gad in the way of <hi>Cain,</hi> and after the error of <hi>Balaam,</hi> who received gifts and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards. You are caſting out your lyes and ſlanders upon the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, but with the light of Chriſt, they are for eternal condemnation, and you that act them, to that in all your conſciences I ſpeak, which ſhall witneſs it eternally, and condemn all you that are acquainted with lyes and ſlanders, for the book of conſcience is opened.</p>
            <p>Prieſts, you ſay, <hi>Paul diſclaims all equality with God,</hi> in your one and twentieth page. Here I charge you to be lyers in the preſence of the living God: <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Let the minde be in you which was alſo in Chriſt Jeſus, who being in the form of God, thought it no robbery to be equal with God, yet made himſelf of no reputation,</hi> &amp;c. Phil. 2. 5 6<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 7.</p>
            <p>Prieſts, and whereas you ſay, <hi>The light which is by Chriſt, is the light of the firſt covenant;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rep.</hi> Chriſt Jeſus ſaith, <hi>He is the light of the world, and doth enlighten every one that comes into the world:</hi> and the Prophet ſaid, <hi>God would give him for a Covenant, a light to the Gentiles:</hi> and here let the Scripture judge you to be out of the light, that ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles at the light and the covenant.</p>
            <p>And whereas you would have <hi>James Nayler</hi> confeſs <hi>George</hi> to be
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:114714:28"/>
the adopted Son of God, what Son was that that was revealed in the Apoſtles? but the confeſſing of the Son of God vexeth you, and ſhews you had not life, for you that have not the Son of God, have not life: Chriſt ſaith, <hi>He is that true light that enlightens every one that comes into the world:</hi> and your anſwer is, <hi>This light is not Chriſts will;</hi> and here you blaſphemouſly declare your ſelves to ſay, The light of Chriſt is not his will; when Chriſt ſaies, <hi>I am the light that enlightens every one that coms into the world,</hi> him that hates it ſhall be his condemnation; and here you ſhew you are in darkneſs that ſtumbles at the light, and your darkneſs cannot compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend it.</p>
            <p>Prieſts, you ſay, <hi>The light of Chriſt is not a knowledge of Chriſt as Mediator.</hi> Here again I charge you to be lyers in the preſence of the living God: whoever comes to know Chriſt as a Mediator, is with the light of Chriſt, which hath enlightned him, and here again I charge you to be ſtumblers at the light.</p>
            <p>And whereas you ſpeak in your ſeven and thirtieth page, of <hi>a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural light,</hi> and ſo blaſpheming the light of Chriſt, but with that light ye ſhall be condemned, before you know the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>Prieſts, in your ſixtieth page you ſay, <hi>Chriſt did not give a ſaving light to every man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rep.</hi> Chriſt the Saviour ſaith, <hi>He enlightens every one that comes into the world and he that walks in the light ſhall bave the light of life, and not walk in darkneſs, and as many as believes in him, and receives him, to them he gives power to become the Sons of God:</hi> but you which ſtumbles at the light of Chriſt and hate it, ſhall be your eternal condemnation, and all your profeſſion to be air, and winde, and empty, and ſhews you do not believe in the light of Chriſt, and ſo with the light you are condemned, and your mouthes ſtopped.</p>
            <p>And whereas you are ſpeaking of your <hi>outward helps and diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries,</hi> or to help the light of Chriſt, here you declare your light to be darkneſs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for the viſible doth not open the inviſible, but the inviſible the viſible, <hi>He that hath an ear to hear<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> let him hear:</hi> but I ſee you have none, that ſtumble at the light of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>You ſpeak of a Trinity<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of ſprinkling Infants, of merits, and of inherent righteouſneſs. I command you to ſhew a word in Scripture that ſpeaks of any of theſe words; you ſpeake of a moral Law, of the word eſſential or ſuggeſtion, ſhew forth where the Scripture
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:114714:28"/>
ſpeaks any ſuch words, ſo take the ſlander upon your ſelves wherewith you ſlander <hi>George Fox,</hi> as jugling, which he abhors, and your ſlander reacheth him not, and ſo finde out theſe words in Scripture, elſe lay your hands on your mouths, and confeſs your ſelves to be jug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers to all the world, and let the Scripture it ſelf judge you, that teach thoſe things there is no Scripture for, who ſaies it is your touch-ſtone and ſtanding oyle; and ſo the title of <hi>Perfect Phariſee</hi> ſhall ſtand to your ſelves, who would be juſtified in the ſight of man, ſo the beaſt ſhall be burned, and the falſe Prophet caſt into the lake of fire.</p>
            <p>The thing that was ſeen concerning <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> all his pillars to be dry, and his trees to be bare, and much nakedneſs, that they have not ſcarcely the bark, but are as a wilderneſs where much winde and cold comes, where there muſt be much labour before the ground be brought into order; for it's a ſtony ground, and there is much bryers and thorns about her, and many trees have grown wilde long, and have ſcarce earth to cover their roots, but their roots are ſeen, and how they ſtand in the ſtones, and theſe trees bears no fruit, but bears moſs, and much winde pierce thorow and clatters them together, and makes the trees ſhake, but ſtill the rootes are held amongſt the ſtones, and are bald and naked.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
